I have a demo of a switch statement
and I'm sort of pulling in some other things that we've already covered, to make the demos a little easier to use.
So for example, it's kind of annoying to have to keep running the demo three, four, five times, to show the
results of three or four different paths through it, I've decided to put this loop in here.
As long as you enter some positive number, let me just follow this brace down, you can see the last thing that
happens in the loop is I'll ask you again for a number, we'll hit the brace bracket, and we'll come back up and
do this while again, and that way with a single run, we can test a number of different values.
So what's happening inside the while loop, well with have this switch statement and we're switching on x, which
is integral type so that's fine. Here's the non-optional open brace and the non-optional close brace at the end
of the switch statement and everything in between is our switch and I have a number of different cases.
So case 1, that is when x = 1, I'll tell you that you entered 1 and I have a break.
Something you'll see quite often is two labels right after each other, so 2 and 3 are right after each other.
This is deliberate and it means that you want to do the same thing for both 2 and 3.
Since we're not doing anything real all I can say is well you must have entered 2 or 3, but imagine a circumstance
where you process both canceled and delayed things the same.
So you might have case canceled: and immediately case delayed and then all the code to handle delayed and canceled
whatever these are. However, sometimes people do it accidently, so I've simulated that accidentalism here
with 4 and 5. There should be a break at the end of case 4 and there isn't and I'll show you happens when the
break is missing and then we have the default. So I'm going to run this through for a whole whack of numbers,
obviously, and let's do that now.
So if I put in 1, it says you entered 1 and that's fine.
If I say 2, you entered 2 or 3 and 3 will also say you entered 2 or 3.
When I say 4, it says you entered 4 you entered 5. Let's flip
back to the code. Because there's no break, it fell through to the 5 case and also executed the case for 5.
probably not what I wanted,
we'll try 5, try something else and finally 0
and we're out. The switch statement certainly takes up a lot less room than many, many nested lsifs and it's more
efficient than just if, if, if, if testing the same thing over and over again.
After all, once we've establish that x is 1 there is no way that it's 4.
Also stacking these up like this, is more readable than combining them with or, you haven't seen combining with or yet,
but trust me this is more readable. So for certain kinds of architecture of your application, the switch statement
is really useful. In modern C++, there are some alternatives especially when you're working with objects and you
variable hierarchies, you can rather than switching on sometimes you can have your objects be of different type
and have an implementation of a virtual function in that type handle whatever this is, so you may not see as
much switch statements, but when you see them I want you to be able to read them and I certainly don't want you
writing big long nested lsifs, when you could've just used a switch.