I'll start with the demo of some free functions.
Here I have a console application, just like all these other console applications, and I've taken the logic for
determining whether something was prime or not and moved it off into a little helper function called is prime.
You can probably guess that it's declared in Utility.h because here's Utility.h, but just to show you how Visual
Studio can help you out, I can right click on this function and Go to the Declaration or the Definition of the function.
If I choose Go to Declaration
you can see here in Utility.h the declaration of the function, it just says there's this function called IsPrime,
it takes an integer, and it returns a Boolean. It doesn't tell you the actual code for it, that would be the
implementation. I can now right click either back in original functions or here and choose Go to Definition
instead of Go to Declaration
and that opens Utility.cpp where the actual implementation of function.
The code for it, it's the for loop from the for demo and it simple returns prime instead of setting a variable
the way the old code did. So this takes an integer, figures out whether it's prime or not, and returns true or false.
Now it has a side effect that it prints on the screen, it's not normal behavior for a function, but this is a demo
it's nice for you to see what's going on, so I left it in there. We go back into
our Main, you can see that we say if IsPrime at x, so that's going to pass x by value down to function which will
return by value true or false back. If I got true back, I'll print out that it's prime, if I got false back I'll
print out that it's not prime. I have a second function called Is2MorePrime and as you can probably guess by looking
at the print outs, it takes x adds 2 to it and sees if that is prime or not.
Why would I write a function like that? Well, I have my reasons. First,
here's the declaration in Utility.h is Is2MorePrime, takes an integer x
and here's the code for it. It makes x 2 larger than it currently is and then passes that down to IsPrime and I
wanted to show you this C++ way of thinking. You don't sort of say Bool 2MoreIsPrime is = to false, 2MoreIsPrime
is = to IsPrime at x and heaven help us, if 2MoreIsPrime is true return true else return false.
You know IsPrime returns a Bool we can just return that ourselves and this sort of chaining up, is a really
common behavior in little helper functions. So return IsPrime at x will call IsPrime passing in the new larger
value of x and get back to our false which will then immediately be returned by Is2MorePrime.
I could have called this whole thing a single line return IsPrime x+2, but I have a second thing I want to show
with this function and that's why it's split out twice. So I'm going to Run it so you can watch it work
and let's try 7. 7 is prime, but as part of processing 7+2 which is 9, we found a factor 3 and so it prints out
7+2 is not prime. This is all good, it's correct behavior.
Now notice that Is2MorePrime changed the value of x to x+2, but when we came back to the
calling code and printed out x it still had the value of 7 and everybody kind of expected that and that was because
x was being passed by value. I'm going to show you how to pass by reference just so that you see the difference.
I have to change here
and say that Is2MorePrime takes an integer reference that's a capital 7 if you're not in the habit of typing them
and that Utility.cpp I have to change in the implementation that it takes an integer reference.
What this means is that the code in Is2MorePrime will actually be working with the same memory slot for x
that this guy is. Not because they have same name, but because it's a reference and so that when it changes it
it will be changing this x and you'll see that if I Run it
if I again enter 7, it correctly finds the factor, it's clearly working with 9, but when we come back it says
9+2 is not prime, which by coincidence 9+2 makes 11, which is prime, but that's not the point, it was testing 9.
The reason it's saying 9+2 is
because it's actually permanently changed x and is now printing out 9 for x.
In this particular case,
we don't want to pass x by reference.
I wanted to show you the consequences of doing it, I'll just build that, but there are times when you do and there
are two times when you want to pass a variable by reference. One is when you want the function to actually change it.
For example, people who write string code, very often want to take a string and maybe capitalize it or change all
e's to w's or whatever and they want to sort of take the string and call this function on it and have the string
end up being changed. The other time you would use pass by reference is when the copy is really expensive, when
you're passing some really large thing and you just don't want to pay for the cost of copying it and then you can
use a reference and there is actually a way to tell the compiler, well yes I am going to take it by reference, but
I promise I won't change it and that will save you from these kinds of accidental mistakes.
We'll be talking about that const, keyword a little later, I just want you to know for now that it exists.
Now I have one more thing going on in here and it's commented out because it is bad and I'm going to uncomment it
out so that you can see
what's bad about it. So I have a function here called BadFunction, which returns and integer reference and I have
the code for it here. I'm using the comment and uncomment buttons in Visual C++ Express, which are super handy
for this kind of thing. It declares this local variable a and returns a reference to a which is to access to the
memory and then when we hit this brace bracket, a goes out of scope and this is what we call a dangling reference
and code that tries to call a BadFunction and use the return value from it, may mostly work, but then on other
occasions it won't work and that's why dangling references can be hard to spot because they don't always fail.
They sort of tend to fail when other code writes over that same address and so you say, wow the value of my variable
changed without me changing it. That's usually caused by problems like a dangling reference.
Compiler as I said on many occasions is your friend. If I just build this using the keystrokes, it's got a warning here,
let's scroll along, returning address of local variable or temporary.
If you see that warning you know you're being warned about a dangling reference and you shouldn't do that.
In this particular case, there's no real reason why this shouldn't just return an integer, integers are cheap to copy.
If you had a different problem there are ways to return references to things that have longer lifetimes, we just haven't
covered that yet,
so it could be possibly correct to return a reference, but never just a reference to a local variable like
a here which you just declared and then it's going to go out of scope when it hits the brace bracket.