Now it all looks fine when someone just shows it to you.
Here is a function being declared, here is a function being implemented, here is a function being called.
Then you get out in the wild and you try to do this yourself and I find often people are really frustrated by the
error messages that they get and the reason for their frustration is that in C++ calling and using a function
requires passing two different checks. Sometimes people are getting message from one check and trying to fix
something that only the other check cares about. It's not going to make the error message go away.
Specifically, you have to make the complier happy, as well as the linker happy.
The compiler only cares that you declared the function, that's usually in a header file.
If you've told the complier, there is a function called, in the case of our free function demo, IsPrime and it takes
an integer, then that will get you no compiler error messages as long as you're calling IsPrime and passing
in an integer, but if you don't implement the function, the linker says I can't find the implementation code for
this to link in. Sometimes people are getting linker error messages and they go and try to change things in a
header file, that's only about the compiler and it's not going to solve your error message.
The easiest way to internalize which error messages are caused by which mistakes is to deliberately make a series
of mistakes and check and see what error messages you get for them and so that's exactly what I'm going to do.
I'm going to use the classes and objects example from the previous demo and deliberately mess up in it a little bit.
So, let's start with getting the name of the function when you're calling it.
So it's declared properly, implemented properly, I'll use get name as an example and I'll just accidently type
the wrong thing and then if I Build the project, I get this error, GetNameX is not a member of Person.
If I double click the error, it repeats the message down here and I can look and see the problem is indeed I've
typed the name of the function wrong. That's easy enough to fix and also I got red wiggles for it, class Person
has no member GetNameX, so I'll fix that.
Our next possible mistake is that I've got the name correct, but I've either used the wrong number parameters or
the wrong type.
Let's go back here and what if I try to pass a number down to GetName.
We don't have a version of GetName that takes a number. You see I get red wiggles, too many arguments in function call.
If I compile anyway, function does not take 1 arguments. Pluralization bugs are fun, aren't they?
Now this applies to also not passing enough arguments or passing the wrong type.
So if come down here to SetNumber and I pass in string instead of a number, it says that the argument is incompatible.
If I build it anyway, so you can see that error message, cannot convert parameter 1, this is actually C++ talk for
that quote string to int and usually that's all the hint you need that oh yeah, this is supposed to take an integer
not a string and you can fix your problem.
Sometimes, you call it properly,
you implement properly, but you mess up when you declare it.
So I'll just put a name change, put an x in the name and we'll build this.
So it's correct in the calling code. It's correct in the implementing code here
in Person.cpp, but the
mistake is in the header file.
Now you notice what happens, I'm getting a very large number of error messages.
For one typo, I'm getting a lot of different error messages and here's why.
These first clump are when I'm compiling that main ClassesandOjects.cpp. ClassesandObjects.cpp tries to call
GetName twice and the error messages are saying there is no GetName.
Now there's an implementation of GetName in the .cpp file, but ClassesandObjects when it's being compiled, the
compiler just looks at what's in the header file Person.h and there's no GetName in the Person.h and so we get a
pair of error messages for the correct lines here, this should be right, but because of the error in the header
file, we're given sort of a false positive error here in our main.
What's more, when we're compiling Person.cpp
and we're trying to implement GetName, it gives us a series of different complaints.
First it says, GetName I don't know what you're talking about and it says that here when we try to call it in the
constructor and the destructor, but it also says it here when we try to implement it.
Plus, it says here, what do you mean firstname, what do mean lastname because as far as the complier is concerned
this function GetName isn't
part of Person and if it isn't part of Person, it doesn't have access to Person's
member variables. So we have this just boat load of error messages all because the compiler doesn't believe that
GetName is part of Person
and so making typos in header files can have dramatic consequences.
Every single file that includes the header file is now going to have some sort of compiler errors and their often
going to be these cascades of errors which say, I don't know what you're talking about plus that's not a member
variable you can't talk to it because you're not part of the class, plus this other code that tries to call the
function is going to get errors and when you fix your one character mistake and rebuild, dozens of error
messages disappear. A good rule of thumb for C++ developers, when you get
a lot of error messages all at once, just fix the first one and then build again because sometimes it'll make a
great number of them go away and that's especially true when the mistake is a mistake in the header file.
Now what if I make a mistake when I'm implementing that function?
So it's declared properly as GetName and it's called
properly as GetName, but I go in here
and I just, you know I'm having a bad day, and I type the name wrong.
I could as easily type the number of parameters wrong or the types of parameters, doesn't matter, you can see right
away I'm getting red wiggles and this is because in the header I said that there was a GetName function, I didn't
say there was a GetNamex function and so just as you saw when the mistake was in the header, this implementation
file is like you're not a member function of person, I don't know what you're talking about and why you think
you're allowed to look at firstname and lastname and you get that big clump, the same clump of error messages
as when the mistake was in the header file.
What if I just flat out forget
to implement the function? You declared it in the header file and you forgot that you needed to implement it.
Especially if you have some functions that are inline, the way GetNumber and SetNumber are, you might type a whole
pile of functions in here and just forget you needed to over and implement GetName.
This is a problem that trips people up because the compiler is going to be perfectly happy.
The compiler when it's compiling
says ClassesandObjects, you notice there's no red wiggles here, GetName is declared in Person.h, but when we Build
these are linker errors and the first linker errors that you'll have seen from me so far.
In fact if you really care, you notice that the error starts LNK.
When you see a linker error, you always look not for a problem in a header file, but for missing implementations.
So the key part of messages it says, unresolved external symbol, something is missing that it was expecting to be
able to find. Now because we're working with strings, this is unfortunate, you sometimes get really nasty error
messages when you're using strings, we'll just skip over all of that.
Here's the important part, Person::GetName. So it's telling you what is missing and then there's some more
decoration which has to do with how overloads are implemented.
Linker error messages reveal a lot of the insides of C++, but you can skip over all that and get to where it turns
into English again referenced in function_wmain, which is what we call it tmain here, but there's a preprocessor thing
that turns in into wmain, that's not terribly vital.
The key is, in amongst all the gibberish, this error message says to you, you said there would be a GetName and
now I can't find it and when you get that error message from the linker, as opposed to the compiler, it's because you
forgot to implement the function. So we quickly implement it, Build it, and we're back to the races again.
What about I wrote it, I implemented it, but I forgot to include the right header file?
That one's the most common mistake actually.
Let's comment out this include of Tweeter and Build.
Here the errors are only in ClassesAndObjects. When you have a mistake in a header file, you get complaints from
ever place that includes that header file. When you forget a header file, you only get the complaints in the place
you forgot it. So here it says Tweeter undeclared identifier and then we have a cascade of errors.
It goes on to say, well if I don't know what Tweeter is then this syntax is really strange I don't know why you've
got round brackets and commas and things, this isn't right and I don't know what t1 is, I'm going to throw this
whole line away, so then a little later it will try to object if you try to talk to t1 because it wasn't properly
declared or it doesn't know its type. The real hallmark you're forgetting and include is that the errors are only
in the file that the include was forgotten in. When the errors are in multiple files, they're caused by a mistake
in the header that's been included into multiple files.
So let's make that right again.
Let's forget the header in the implementation file now.
So if I go into Person.cpp
because I happen to have it open, scroll up to the top, and forget to include Person.h.
Now when this is being complied, I'm declaring all these member functions in the person class.
In fact, I'm even declaring the fact that there is a Person class in a file that's not being included into here
and as you can see from all the red wiggles, in here they're like why are trying to talk about Person.
anything that's got :: after it has to be a class name.
This is your clue that the complier doesn't think Person is a class name and here, it says I don't know what GetName
is and GetName is a member of function of Person, but the compiler no long knows that because you didn't include
it here in the implementation file. So if I build it, tons of errors, all coming from Person.cpp and basically
starting with this one, Person is not a class or namespace name.
The rest of these kind of cascade from that. You notice eventually it does give up, it says wow, you are so messed
up I'm going to stop even trying to figure out what you mean and that's a good sign.
You don't work your way up from the bottom or pick one of these things in the middle and try and fix it, you start
with the first error, Person is not a class or namespace name, well I declared the Person to be a class over in
Person.h, I forgot to include Person.h, fix it up, build it and all the errors go away.
Finally, one that's not very likely to happen as long as you're following along the way I told you how to add classes
into your project, but that can trip you up, so
I'll show it to you. When you look in this project, we have files over here in the Solution Explorer.
When this project was built, it was built two different ways, one by right click, Add, a Class, which added a
cpp and an h file at the same time and one by right click Add, New Item twice, once by choosing cpp file and once
choosing header file and both of these approaches add the cpp file to the project.
It doesn't much matter whether a header file is included in the project or not, but it really matters that an
implementation is added to the project. If you right click any of these file tabs, you can choose Open
Containing Folder and in here
you will see the cpp files and the h files all mixed together and you could, if you wanted to, right click and
Create a File here, typically people would create a Text Document and then rename it with a different extension,
and that would add a file to this folder, but it wouldn't add the file to the project.
Sometimes people give you code, and you just put it in the folder and if you forget to add it to the project
the includes will work because includes follow a path and just look on that path for a file with that name, but
the linking will not because unless the cpp file is explicitly added to the project, it won't be linked into the project.
So to simulate forgetting to add, I'm going to remove a file from the project and I'm going to remove Tweeter.cpp
with this Exclude From Project. Now you see that it disappears from here, it's still
in the folder, nothing's happened to the actual file and if I Build this
again we're getting linker errors, they start LNK unresolved external symbol and it's actually complaining about
two different things, one is the destructor and the other is the constructor of Tweeter.
They're both caused because the cpp file, Tweeter.cpp, is no long being linked into the project.
Now, as long as you always add new material by right clicking your project and choosing Add, you will get things
added to your project because you're busy adding them to your project.
Should it ever happen that someone gives you a file of code and especially if you then get an error like this,
we'll say, I've got to add it to the project, you can choose to Add Existing Item.
It'll start by default looking right in the folder with the rest of your code.
There's Tweeter.cpp and get it Added
back into the project, shows up here, and I can Build and the Build succeeds.
Should it happen that you get linker errors and you're sure the code is in the file, the next step is, is the linker
including the file and the way to test that is to look over here in Solution Explorer and make sure that the cpp
file really is in the project and not just in the solution that the project is part of.
Now you've seen the full spectrum of mistakes a person can make when their working with functions whether you
make a mistake calling it, declaring it, or implementing it.
You've seen the difference between compiler error messages and linker error messages.
You understand that sometimes you get dozens of error messages from a single character mistake and that noticing
whether your error messages come all from the same file or from a variety of different files, is an excellent way
to zero in on exactly where you're problem is. I hope this makes the process of fixing error messages a lot less
frustrating for you.