I mentioned it's very non C++ to say if x = true return true else return false, you would just say return x
and similarly, certain kinds of constructs around if's where all you're doing is setting the value of a single
variable, they set some C++ developers teeth on edge and they prefer to use an immediate if.
So this isn't wrong. If whatever result = 7 else result = 302, the complier will like it, it'll execute just fine
there's no speed hit from doing it, but many people prefer to use this notation, result = something?, that's how
you're supposed to pronounce it, 7 and then the : you can pronounce else 302.
These mean exactly the same thing. If something evaluates to true, result will get set to 7.
If something evaluates to false, result will get set to 302 and it just takes a single line instead of four lines
to get your expression across. There's not constraints on what you can put in there.
You could say 7, but you could also call something along function.
You can say 302, but you could again call some big long function if calculations whatever you want.
As a best practice, it's more readable if at least one of them is just a simple literal, but you can use the same
kinds of things that you could use if you wrote it out the long way, it's simply a matter of syntax.