A simple demo for an immediate if.
To make it not entirely trivial, I also thought I'd show you another idiom for the let's keep going until someone
enters their signal value to quit. I showed you before with the switch, we first prompted the person, enter a
number, then we went into the loop, and then we did the prompting again at the bottom of the loop.
The other possibility is to put the prompting in the loop, then you have to initialize the variable to what we
call a signal value. Something that will make sure you go into the loop.
So here, we're setting x=99 and then saying while &gt; 0, which of course it will be for sure the first time.
Then we can go through and process our number. There are some other ways to move the test to the end, but you'll
see this pattern fairly often and sometimes people are confused they're like you set it 99 and then you immediately
check whether it was &gt; 0, of course it's &gt; 0, yes, but you'll be guaranteed they'll be some code inside the loop
that will change it and that way you're going to go into that loop at least once, but you don't know how many times.
That's the while part. Here's the immediate if part. Here's the ?.
So we're declaring a string which we're calling sign and we're giving it the value all in this single line of code.
We're saying, is x&gt;0? And you don't pronounce it, that's what the ? is supposed to help you do.
Is x&gt;0? If it is, sign will end up saying positive if it's not then sign will end up saying 0 or negative.
Then we're just going to print out your number is and that string variable sign.
Easy enough, let's run this one a couple times
So if I say 55, you're number is positive. Excellent. -11, your number is 0 or negative and then it's done
It's a very simple little thing. Mostly what it is, is people say what, where did this ? or why is there are :
in the middle of this statement, now you know that's an immediate if.