C++ Flow of Control expressions really aren't that complicated, but you can build really complicated applications
out of them. The existence of an if of a loop of some kind, that's common throughout languages.
Maybe different languages call them different things, but they all pretty much exist.
If you are muddled up a little bit on where do the brace brackets go, how come sometimes I have to have them and
sometimes I don't? Remember the compiler is your friend.
So in the for loop, the three parts are separated with semicolon.
If you separate them with something else, you'll get message saying that some of them are missing.
You'll have to interpret that, that because I don't have semicolon's it thinks this is all just the initializer
and it's yelling me about the other pieces no being there.
Typically, commas is what people do wrong there. Switch your commas to semicolons and your error messages will go away.
Same if you leave out your braces or some other part of the syntax of your switch statement.
You can build a for loop with a while. You say that they were pretty much interchangeable.
You can build a switch out of a bunch of if's and else's.
You can certainly build an immediate if out of an if and an else, and in fact, especially if you were to drag the
dreaded goto into the mix, you could get by without anyone of them replacing them with the other instead.
So use them in the way that's most readable, and in the way that most C++ developers use them.
So for example, if you know how many time you're going to go through a loop, you should use for.
For int i=0, i &lt; 10 increment i by 1, that's just a common or guarded loop.
You can do it with a while, but people would think you were kind of strange.
When you don't know how many time you're going to through in advance because you're processing a whole file or
you're keeping going until the user presses 0, use a while.
The complier couldn't care less what you use, but humans who read your code do.
Should you use a switch or a bunch of if's, assume there's just more than three possibilities or even really three
go with the switch. If there's just two, don't make a switch for just two, that's kind of weird, that's like an
if and it's else. You don't need that. Should you use an immediate if?
Well the minute your immediate if has to spend multiple lines, you're probably doing it wrong.
The whole point of the immediate if is it took that for line construct and turned it into a one line construct.
If your conditions and your values that you're setting the variable to are so long that the whole thing has to be
broken up with line breaks, it should probably be a regular if.
We also talked about functions, about free functions and member functions.
Taking parameters by values or by reference and return by value or by reference.
The demos I've showed you where all the parameters are return types are things like integers, you know what, just
always do it by value, but there will be times when taking by reference is appropriate and you've seen the syntax
now that capital 7 that &amp; after the type integer reference.
You can also have string reference, or person reference, we just didn't happen to demo them.
Functions are what your application is built up, functions and classes.
Your functions are built out of these Flow of Control constructs, out of loops, out of conditionals, out of checking
to see if something is found or done, or good enough, or needs special handling.
You're almost complete versed in all of the C++ syntax and ready to start putting this all into action.