Flow of Control is just about which lines in your program execute in what order.
Normally speaking, control flows from one line to the next, integer x = 2, x = 3, print something out showing the
value of x and they all just happen in that order, but just about every programming language has some way to
change that around and you should probably recognize things like if, and while, you can also call a function.
They're pretty simple things to get, the trick maybe is the syntax and the C++ syntax I'll show you in working code,
so that you can see how it's done and remember as I like to say, the complier is your friend so that if you mess
up and leave off some brackets, you'll get an error message, then you'll know what to do about it.
Things that are a little difficult in C++, there are a for loop, not every language has a for loop.
The switch statement and the Immediate if. I also want to talk about the break, which is relevant in while and
for and a few other places and I'm just going to mention that goto exists.
I don't have a goto demo, I don't want you to use goto, it's there if you happen to read, is a goto, but all those
years ago we said goto is considered harmful and for those who aren't in on the joke consider harmful has really
become the nastiest insult you can give a language feature.
I'm not going to show you how to use it, I don't want you to use it, it does just for the sake of technical
accuracy, does exist, that's all I want to say about goto.