Let's begin with if. Like all keywords in C++, it's spelled all lowercase and the syntax is if round bracket,
some condition and round bracket what to do if that condition is true.
The round brackets are not optional, if you leave them out you're going to get a syntax error.
Your condition could be something like x is &gt; than 0, y+2 is &gt; than some function or another, any expression you
like and you can test against things that are not Boolean values.
You can test against numbers and it's quite common actually to see C++ people do that.
When somebody tests against 7, or variables that are not Booleans, their converted to Booleans using the rules
we talked about before, 0 is false, everything else is true, going to the if or not.
So for example if x&gt;3, y=7. You can put a line break in there if you like, like this, they're both exactly the
same complier couldn't care less and it's important to note, compiler does not read indents and doesn't understand
anything special, based on whether or not you indent the lines, those are for humans.
So if you're going to have your action across multiple lines you have to enclose it in braces and I prefer to use
them even for a single line, like this. If x&gt;3 .
The reason I prefer them is simple. When you go and add a second line, you can add it between the braces and
it'll still works. If you just add a second line when you didn't have any braces and you forget to add them, you get
weird bugs because nobody complains, but the second line gets executed every single time regardless of whether
the if is true or not. So as a best practice, always have braces even when there's only a single line in your action.
Now you can have an else clause if you like, it just goes immediately after the if and if has all the same rules
about single line, multiple line with braces, best practices to have braces.
You don't have to have an else if you don't want to.
If you have a lot of ifs and elses all kind of muddled up together, sometimes the complier can match ifs up with
the wrong else, braces can help there to make it really clear what your intent is.