I have a super quick demo to show you and because I've not covered all of the C++ operators, I'm just going to keep
using &gt;, I think it's pretty readable and obvious how &gt; works and that'll make the demo perhaps not utterly
thrilling, but at least we'll be able to focus on how if works and how else works.
So let's come over into Visual C++
Express. You can see that I'm going to ask you to enter two numbers.
We're going to use standard see n to get those values and I'm not doing any error checking or validation about
whether you went through numbers or letters or anything like that because that's not the point of this particular demo.
So it's not going to work right if you don't work it right, so I have a simple if, if x &gt; y, we'll put out that
it's larger and it has an else and I've put braces around both clauses even though they're only a single line just
because I feel that a best practice. Now a momentary word about bracing style.
People have arguments about braces positioning that far exceed the arguments that they can have about politics,
or religion, or any other major touch points and I'm not going to go there.
The bracing style I'm using is the default in Visual Studio.
You can tell Visual Studio if you have a different style.
So some people prefer to indent the braces so they line up here with the contents of the if and some people like to
put the first braces up here on the same line as the if.
I'm not going to argue the pros and cons, there are many different bracing styles.
If you're working for a company that has a style guide, follow the style guide for your bracing.
If you're updating someone else's code, do not go in there and "fix" that person's bracing style while you're making
whatever changes your making. For one thing, it makes difs very difficult when you go through the source control
to decide what was done, but also the chances are the next person's just going to "fix" it right back again.
So don't get into a brace alignment war, what I'm showing you here is what Visual Studio does if you don't tell
it any differently and if you have to use a different style, get Visual Studio to help with that by changing the
options so that it respects your particular bracing style.
Really simple test, here's an if with an else and if I just scroll down a little further, I want to show you that
you can have an if without an else if you want and you also can have a single line without braces.
The reason that I like to have braces no matter what is because people tend to believe that if they came here
and wrote some other line like change y=3 when the total is &gt; 10, that it somehow is associated with the if, but it isn't.
Only the line immediately after the if is executed just when the if is true.
So this y=3 line would get executed every time, whether the if was true of false and we say the complier doesn't
read indents. Since I started saying that many years ago, languages have been invented that do read indents, but
C++ isn't one of them. So if you always have braces, then when you add another line it will naturally get caught up
and this is just a mistake and you don't want to do it.
It's a pretty simple program, it's going to run. It'll print out is larger than or is not larger than and in the
case, that I happen to choose two numbers that add to more than 10, it'll also print this extra piece of information.
I'm going to Run it a few times so that you can see. So I'll run with Ctrl+F5
and if I enter 4 and 5, it prints out 4 is not larger than 5, that's right, and 4+5 is only 9, so we didn't get
the extra thing about thanks for
large numbers. Let's just run it again
6 is larger than 4, 10 is not larger than 10, so we still don't get
that message and I run it one more time
55 is not larger than 66, thanks for choosing larger numbers!
So I hope no one's really surprised to learn how if's work in C++, they work as they do in whatever language you
happen to know and as you can see, you can have more complex expressions in those round brackets if you want them
I'm just happening to choose simple expressions because it makes the demos simple.