Flipping over to Visual Studio
I have a really simple application that asks you for a number and I'm going to work out if it's prime or not.
So I'm going to assume it's prime and then I'm going to go through a while loop looking for factors.
If I find a factor, it's not prime. If I come all the way through the while loop and didn't find a factor, it
must still be prime. I'm using a different operator, I'm using &lt;=, hopefully everyone can recognize that and this
is a bit of a trick if you haven't done a lot of calculating of primes.
It's enough to go until the number you're testing as a factor is larger than if I were to divide that number into
the original number. So in the case of 102, if I divide 51 into it, getting 2, 2 is less than 51 so I've already
tried the other half of the factor in other words. So it's just a little optimization to make your loop go faster
and I am really only including it so that you can again see that we can have more complex constructs in our
conditions for our whiles. So what do I do each time I go through this loop?
I try to figure out what the factor would be and I'm taking something that's almost certainly not an integer and
putting it into an integer. We talked about this in data types, that's going to silently truncate the result,
which is exactly what I want. So if I'm testing whether or not 2 goes into 7, I'll take 7 divide it by 2, get
3 and a bit, that'll get truncated out to 3. Then on the next line, I multiple it back 3*2 is 6 which is not
= to 7, so in this case, this if would fail and we would come out.
When it does =, it's because the numbers actually a factor.
Now we'll take more about operators later, but I do want to show you the == being used for testing equality in C++.
Something in the operators section we'll take more about that, just pointing it out here.
So if we did find a factor, we'll print that out, normally apps don't, but I'm trying to be transparent here and
set out Boolean prime to false. Super important if you're going to do a loop with a while you have to do something
to move you towards getting out of the loop. If you're looping while you read a file, you should read another
line of the file. If you're looping while you're process a data set, you should move onto the next row of the
data set and so on. Here, I'm just going to increment i. There are better ways to increment i, but those can
wait for the operators material. That's the loop, once we come out the other end, we can test that Boolean variable
prime and print out using our new found skills whether it's prime or not and that's the whole application.
So I'm going to Run it
let's test 7, 7 is prime.
Let's run it again.
Let's test 25, 25 has a factor, it makes sense, 25's not prime.
Now, I have a little bit of an optimization in this app in that I only go up as high as I need to and not all the
until I've tested up to the value X of the number of I put it, but I have an inefficiency still in place.
Let's try running one more time and this time I'll put in 12, a number that
has a lot of factors. You see it finds the factor 6 and 4, it concludes that 12 is not prime, but as soon as we
found the first factor 6, we knew 12 wasn't prime, there's no need to continue to go and find other factors. I can
make this exit once it's understood that this isn't a prime number.
This is a great use of the break keyword. Break gets you out of the loop you are in.
So here, it doesn't get it out of ifs of anything, it gets you out of whiles and when we do fors, it also gets
you out of fors and some other constructs. So what'll happen is if we find a factor, we'll break out of the
while loop and rather than incrementing i and going to back up to test again whether or not i is still less divided
by the new i, we'll just come straight out to the line after the close brace of the while and this just makes the
code in this example a little more efficient. You wouldn't do this if you wanted to find every one, but it's a common
idiom to have to find the first of something and this is a simple way to stop, once you have found that first one.
So I'll Run it
and again, we'll do 12. This time it only finds the factor 6, it doesn't go on and find the factor of 4 because
break took us out of the while.
You can see that once you know if, you also really know a lot of the rules around while, pretty straightforward.