In addition to while, C++ also has the for loop. For loops are made up of three parts.
There's the initializer that starts the beginning of the loop.
So if you want to do something 10 times you might initialize to 1, if you were going to go from 1 to 10 or to 0
if you're going to go from 0 to 9. You can declare a database here in the initializer.
If you do that, then the variable goes out of scope when the for loop is over or you can use a variable that's
already in scope and it will continue to be in scope at the end of loop.
Next, we have a condition using exactly the same kinds of expressions you can use for if and while.
That means Boolean expressions but also things that evaluate to something other than a Boolean and then we have
the loop expression, the thing that moves you onto the next item in the loop.
So in our while, we have to remember by hand at the bottom of the loop to put i = i + 1 and you'll sometimes see while
loops where the increment is in the middle, especially if it's something like reading a file.
The for loop expression is always done as the very last thing, so the whole loop body gets executed and then the
loop expression, and then we come around and test the condition again and if appropriate go and execute the loop again.
So here's a sample for loop for int i=0, i &lt; 10; i = i + 1 and again, there's a better way to increment i, which
we'll cover later. Now this loop runs from 0 to 9, 10 is not less than 10 and running from 0 to 9 is the very C++
way to do something 10 times. Because i has been declared right here in the initializer, after the for loop i
will be out of scope. That's great, it lets you sort of throw away these variables whenever you want.
Sometimes people want to use the loop variable afterwards. In that case, you need to declare it on the line before
int i and then 4 i = 0, i &lt; 10 and so on.