Because for and while are so similar, I took the while example and
rewrote it as a for example,
so I didn't have to explain it again. Enter a number and now I'm using a for loop int i=2.
I don't need i after the loop so I'm declaring it right there.
The condition and the increment are what you recognize from the while.
You're much less likely to forget to increment and accidently write an infinite loop when you use a for loop, by the way.
The body's exactly the same and we can break out of a for the same as we can break out of a while and the printing
out exactly the same. So let's run this.
We'll enter a number, let's try 25, 25 is not a prime.
Hopefully, no one is surprised by any of these results.
Let's try another one, 7 is
prime and just to demonstrate breaking out of the for loop
let's choose a number with plenty of factors, let's try 24 this time instead of 12.
First factor it finds when it's trying to, it finds 12, not prime, breaks out of the for loop.
So there you go. They're not importantly different to the compiler.
For and while are importantly different to people and the ability to control that scope to have the loop variable
disappear after the loop is a big plus for many people.
They don't really want to liter their code with a bunch of different loop variables, i, j, k, ii, jj, so being
able to use one like this, that comes into scope and goes out of scope, and be a highly useful thing, and I have a
little more guidance a little later on about for versus while.