Switch really solves only one problem, but it's a problem that happens a lot, it's a pattern that's super common
in your applications and that's when you basically have a whole pile of ifs because you're trying to figure out
which condition you're in. So affects is 1, do something or another affects is 2 do something or another, affects
3, do something else and it's a little inefficient to do it that way because the compiler would keep testing.
Once you know that x is 1 it can't possibly be 2 or 3, and yet you're testing your ifs over and over, so then people
write nested ifs. So they write if x is 1 do this else, brace bracket, if x is 2 do this else and you sort of
nest and nest and nest it, it gets really hard to read.
The switch statement is just a cleaner version that people can clearly follow.
Here's the syntax, other languages have this, but the exact word that's used varies from language to language.
Where the brackets and braces and what not also very vary, so we have round brackets around the expression, just
as with an if, just as with a while. Must have a and open brace immediately after that and a closed one, not optional
and then you have one or more case statements and each one of them is case value: what to do and then a break,
and optionally at the end of it all, you can have a default: and what to do.
If you leave the break off, control just falls down and executes the next case for you, which is sometimes what
you want, usually not what you want. Then you have a closed brace at the end of the whole thing to say okay, I'm
all done with the switching. You don't have to have a default, so it's not like the complier can say, I processed
the default, so I must be done, it needs that to let it know.
You don't put brace brackets after each case because you keep going until you hit the break, so there's no need for
braces after each individual case statement. The expression you're switching on, needs to work out to an integer.
It's very common to switch on the value of a single variable, but it could be some expression or in a enum,
which are integers behind the scenes and the individual case statements you're testing against integer values
also or enum values.