I'm going to start by showing you manual memory management when there
aren't member variables, when you're just working with local storage that has pointers to something on the
free store, and those pointers can go out of scope when your local function ends.
That will be the start of our complications.
Here I'm using a class called Resource. It's very simple. It just has a string in it.
It has a constructor that takes a string and I'll show you the code in a second, but it sticks it in this
variable, not surprisingly, and a destructor, and it has a GetName that gives you that string back.
The constructor does initialize the string, as I mentioned, and it also prints something out, and the
destructor prints something out, so we can do some lifecycle tracking.
First, I'm going to create a Resource locally on the stack, as it were, and I'll call its GetName using the
dot notation and then when we hit this brace it'll go out of scope and you'll see it go out of scope and the
destructor run. Just a reminder of how local variables go out of scope when they hit their close brace.
Then, I'm going to create a Resource on the free store using operator new.
That gives me back a Resource pointer, which I'm putting in as variable pResource, and I'm going to use the
arrow notation to call this member function GetName on pResource.
Then, I'm going to start doing bad things. The first bad thing I'm going to do is I'm going to make a copy
of pResource, put it in this other Resource pointer called p2, and I'll call GetName on that to prove it's
still working and then I'll use delete to delete pResource. The first thing I'm going to do is try to use a
pointer that I just called delete on, let you see what happens. Then, I'm going to set that to nullptr and
delete it again, and then I'm going to try calling p2, and p2 is pointed to some memory on which delete has
already been run. This is quite a collection of badness. What's going to happen is I'm going to run it;
it's going to blow up; we'll look at the error; I'll comment out the bad line; we'll go like one line further
and get the error again, and so on, so let's begin.
Free store has stopped working. How far did we get before we stop working?
Well, you notice we constructed the local and then destructed it, and we constructed the created with new
and then we destructed it.
In other words, we got past here. It was no problem trying to get these values from p2 or pResource into
these local strings. We deleted this pResource. That caused the destructor to print out that it had cleaned
it up, and then when we tried to do this it blew up, and I can prove that quickly with the debugger.
I'll put the break point right here and just run to the break point.
Okay, we're fine to here.
There's some very small output there and when I step over
this is where we blow up. When you do this under the debugger the error messages are a little different.
You get unhandled exception, bad_alloc. It can be a little harder to read, so I've been trying not to get it
to blow up under the debugger, but that's where we were when it blew up.
I'm going to stop debugging
and close the random piece of the
Standard Library that we ended up in. We blew up because of this line,
of trying to call GetName on pResource when pResource has been deleted.
Let's do that and I'll run it again. (Typing)
Oh, this is quite bad, right? We got into a destructor, obviously.
It's printing out, destructing, but when it tried to get a hold of the name that's when it blew up.
I happen to know which of these two deletes caused the problem and again, I can show you which by using the
debugger. (Typing)
Okay, we're fine till here. We set pResource to a nullptr. We try to delete a nullptr; that's harmless.
You can do that all you want. Delete basically says, is it already nullptr, okay never mind and returns.
Nothing bad happens, but when we go to delete p2
that's when the bad thing happens and it's simply that
p2
is pointing to memory that's
already been cleaned up and calling delete on it again, it is bad.
Now just to prove that it's not the copy that's the problem, I'm going to comment out this line that sets
pResource to nullptr. And now if I run, let's move the breakpoint, (Typing)
this lines going to make it go boom, and it does.
Deleting something that's already been deleted is a bad and dangerous thing to do.
If you set it to nullptr it's safe. Here, p2 points to the same place that pResource points to and so, once
you've deleted pResource, trying to delete p2 is exactly the same as trying to delete pResource twice.
You might think that you would never make these mistakes, trying to talk to an object after you've already
deleted it, deleting it twice, those sorts of things. Alright, I'll believe that.
Let's comment out all this weirdness (Typing) and just run this to prove that we are currently a balanced
application. (Typing)
We construct the local one on the stack and then destruct it when it goes out of scope.
We construct the free store one by calling new and it gets deleted exactly once; nobody blows up;
everybody's happy. Huh. Who said this memory management stuff was tough?
I don't know what you're talking about. Well I tell you what, let's just do something relatively mild here.
I'm going to make myself an integer and I'm going to make a test to see if that integers 3, and you can tell
that it is, and I'm going to return from my function early if it's 3.
It could happen. Here's what's going to happen. We will call new and then we will return and we will never
delete it. If I run this (Typing)
there's no error; there's no blowing up, but do you see what happened?
We constructed and destructed local, but we only constructed the created with new.
We never destructed it. That's a memory leak. Now this application is about to end,
so you know, what harm did the memory leak do? But in a real application if this wasn't my main, but a
function that processed something, and if Resource was 1,000 bytes, 10,000 bytes, could easily be, and I leak
that many bytes out of the free store, sooner or later when another part of my code tries to get memory from
the free store it's going to be told, there isn't any, and that's when the application hangs, and well,
back in the day we used to have to reboot the whole machine, but you're still at least going to have to end
task your application. Memory leaks can be really crippling and memory leaks happen when you don't delete
something. We have code to delete it, but that code doesn't execute because we bailed out in the middle of
the function and occasionally, in this material, I refer to exceptions.
You may say I'm never going to write return in the middle of a function.
Exceptions can do that to you, so you have to think about how can you write your code in such a way
that it works even if someone bails out in the middle of a function?
Now here, my pointers, pResource, p2, they're local variables, not going anywhere.
They don't have a long life themselves, although they point to long-lived things out on the free store.
Things get a little weirder when you put a pointer as a member variable of a class.
Here, I'm working with the Person class again, but this Person is a little bit changed from the Person that's
been kicking around for so long and I want to show you how it looks.
Person, in addition to a first name, a last name, and an arbitrarynumber now has a Resource pointer.
When I construct a Person I set their Resource pointer to nullptr.
Now this particular idiom is one that you would use if something is optional.
You might have a Resource or you might not. When you don't have a Resource the pointer is nullptr.
When you do have a Resource the pointer points to the one Resource that you have.
We have a member variable in Person
called AddResource and this member function
creates a new Resource and puts that resulting pointer into this member variable, pResource.
Here, I make myself a local Person. I'm going to call AddResource and then I guess my work is done.
Let's see what happens.
Constructing Resource for Kate Gregory and we're done, so this is a memory leak.
We never destructed it. That was foolish.
Now there's nothing wrong with allocating my Resource out on the free store with new.
In fact, it's the only way that I can get a Resource that lives longer than this function.
If I just created some local variable (Typing)
and then said the pResource (Typing) is equal to the address of r,
the minute we come out of scope here, (Typing) r goes out of scope.
It's cleaned up, and pResource is now pointing to something that's been cleaned up
and you saw how badly that worked out in the other demo where trying to talk to something that's already been
cleaned up causes crashing. You can't do this.
You want a Resource that lives out on the free store so that it lives longer than AddResource function runs.
So the solution to the memory leak is there needs to be a delete somewhere, so we can
go into the destructor for Person and say, (Typing) cleanup that pResource pointer.
That's all. I don't need to check to see if it's okay to delete it or not because it started out as nullptr,
and as I mentioned, you can call delete on nullptr and it's harmless.
So I'll just call delete on it because nullptr nothing will happen, but if it was set with AddResource
it'll call delete on it. Let's run this.
One constructing, one destructing. We're back in balance. Hooray.
That works, but only because the person who wrote the main hasn't done anything bad yet.
What I want to do is to write a Person class that is thoroughly robust to people doing, well bad's not the
right word, ordinary stuff that happens to be dangerous, running with scissors as it were.
Here's one thing a person might do, they might call AddResource twice.
Probably not on consecutive lines like this, but if it's a big, complicated application with lots of code
passed through it, and it happens to come across the AddResource call more than once, what is my app going to
do about that? And here, to make it easier to tell them apart, let's call SetName, (Typing)
so that the Resources, they build their name from the name of the Person
and we'll be able to tell them apart. I'll run these,
and we're back to having a memory leak. We constructed the first one for Kate, then we constructed a second
one for Kate2, and we ended up only cleaning up the one for Kate2.
The one for Kate is just sitting out there still on the free store forever, causing a memory leak.
Why? Because we gave this the name AddResource and that's what it does.
It just adds another Resource out on the free store for us. It should probably have a different name.
I'm going to leave its name alone, but I'm going to fix its code.
If there is an existing pResource already, we need to get rid of it; clean it up.
I'm just going to copy this line from the destructor. (Typing)
Again, if pResource is nullptr this is harmless,
but if there is a pResource this'll clean it up and then we'll new up a fresh one.
Let's test it.
Much better. We're back in balance. We construct the Kate, clean it up, construct the Kate2, and,
eventually, clean that up when the Person object goes out of scope and its destructor cleans up its
Resource.
Okay, we're starting to create a person class that is managing this Resource appropriately,
but again, we need to be
robust to the sorts of things that people might do when they're consuming our Person class, so
here's another behavior that maybe you didn't count on. I am making a copy of Kate and putting it in another
Person object called Kate2. The compiler will actually construct a Kate2 object and copy each member
variable over from Kate to Kate2. That's the default behavior.
The first name will get copied over, the last name, the arbitrarynumber, and the pResource pointer,
and then you know what's going to happen? When we hit this close brace right here
this Person object's going to go out of scope and this Person object is going to go out of scope.
The first one who goes out of scope will delete pResource. That's great.
Clean up the free store; life is good. Then, the other one will go out of scope and will also
attempt to clean up the very same thing. It's just like over here
in this example where we deleted pResource and then we deleted the copy of it, p2.
Here, on code you don't see, when Kate and Kate2 go out of scope they will each try to delete their own copy
of that pointer. The second one, well, it's not going to be good.
There we go. We're tucking along nicely, but we have that extra destructing and it's blown up -- exactly the
same problem. We're trying to delete something twice.
What can we do to protect ourself against somebody doing this? You could say, no copying people.
The Person class is not for copying and there's even a way that you can get the compiler to help you with
that, but I'm going to guess that that's probably not a rule you want to impose.
After all, it would make it impossible to pass it to a function by value, for example.
We have to teach the system how to copy Person objects safely and we do that by writing what's called a copy
constructor. I'm going to go into Person
and here, with the existing constructor that we already have, I'm going to add another constructor. (Typing)
You know it's a constructor. It doesn't have a return type and it takes a const Person reference p.
Now I need to implement my
copy constructor. (Typing)
I'm going to copy this one, but my parameters is not all these individual bits and pieces, (Typing)
so const Person reference p. (Typing)
And I'm going to initialize using the member variables of p. (Typing)
Finally, for pResource, I don't want to copy over p's pResource.
I could, but that's the problem that got us here, right?
This is what the compiler generated for me automatically. I need to do something better.
In fact, what I need to do is make my own Resource up on the free store and have a different pointer that
points to that different resource on the free store. Now that different Resource can have the same values
in it, so what I'm going to initialize this to is a new Resource, and remember it takes a string.
I'm going to get the string by calling old p's pResource's GetName. (Typing)
This copy constructor will just bitwise copy over the other three member variables; they're harmless, they're
just strings of numbers. And for pResource I'm going to ask the old pResource for its name and pass that in
when constructing a brand new pResource of my own. Okay. Let's give it a whirl.
You can see that we are paired up nice and neat -- constructing, destructing,
two constructing's, two destructing's. Everything's in balance. There's no leak.
We're not blowing up,
so we got through this person choosing to construct a fresh Person object from the Person object we already
had. That's not the only kind of copying that happens. There's also, what's called the Copy Assignment, so
if I take my existing, fully-constructed Kate, which has a Resource, and assign it to Kate2, which is also
fully-constructed and has a Resource, the copy constructor is not what makes this happen.
What makes this happen is the assignment operator. That's an overloaded operator just like operator&lt; or
operator &gt; or operator += and the other operators we've talked about, and that, by default _____ a
bitwise copy, and I guess you know what that means. It'll copy the pointer over and when they go out of
scope they'll both have the same pointer
and we'll well go boom.
Just like that.
In order to protect against this behavior we have to write an overload of assignment operator.
I'll put that down here with the other operators and the signature, rather like the signature of
the copy constructor, it's not yours to choose. This is the signature of an assignment operator.
It returns a Person reference, that's so you can write x = y = zed, and its name is operator= and it takes a
const Person reference p. Now let's implement it. (Typing)
I need to get the pieces over and this is a handy way to do it. (Typing)
I can't use the initializer syntax in an operator overload the way I can in a constructor,
but I can just reduce my typing this way. (Typing)
Here I'm copying the three member variables over, p.firstname, p.lastname, p.arbitrarynumber being copied
into the appropriate member variables here, and I can new up a pResource, but there's something I have to do
first. In the case where we were using the copy
constructor, here, Kate2 was not already constructed and obviously didn't have a pResource.
But here, where we're going in the other direction, Kate has a pResource that's pointing to something
on the free store and if I wipe that
value of pResource out, putting in the pointer I get from this second called a new, I'm never going to free
the old stuff. So before, I new up something to put into pResource I've got to delete what is already in
There. And again, remember if it was a nullptr that's fine; that's harmless.
Almost forgot, we have to return something and the equals operator always returns *this.
We've come all this way and never talked about this yet. This is a pointer that all member functions have
secretly available, but because we haven't been living a very pointery life we haven't used it yet, that
represents the object itself. When this line of code runs
Kate = Kate2, this will point to Kate. When Kate.SetFirstName runs
this will point to Kate and when Kate.AddResource runs it will point to Kate.
If somebody called Kate2.SetName, this would point to Kate2 during that execution of SetName.
It's, in fact, the mechanism by which member functions can get to the right member variable.
This is a pointer. We don't return a pointer; we return a reference, so we dereference it with star.
Star this, that's what usually return from an operator equals. Now let's run it. (Typing)
We have four pairs and they match up. We construct and destruct here.
Then we have two constructs, one destruct, so a net of one, another construct, so for a net of two, and then
two destructs. No leaks. No booms.
We have finally constructed a fully robust Person class.
Because Person had a meaningful destructor, we had to write a meaningful copy constructor,
and a meaningful operator= or assignment operator, two names for the
same thing, and I will not deny to you, this is totally work.