Are you thinking, there must be a better way? You're darn right there must be a better way.
Listen, if you're a library writer maybe you would deal with this, but in your regular, everyday life just
writing a Person class there is such a nicer way to do it. You see, C++, especially C++ 11, has what are
known as smart pointers. Smart pointers are objects that you allocate in local storage, on the stack, as a
member variable, whatever. They're solid objects. They're not pointers, despite their names.
They have a pointer inside them. When the smart pointer goes out of scope you know what his destructor does?
He calls delete for you. It's such a simple thing. It's actually templated.
It'll work with any kind of pointers. A T pointer, so you can give it an integer pointer or a Person pointer
or a Resource pointer, Employee pointer, whatever, and when you construct it it keeps a copy of that pointer.
When it goes out of scope the destructor does delete on that pointer.
No memory leak and it can't happen twice. It can't happen two few times, too many times. You're safe.
What about the copying and the assigning? Well, there are different kinds of smart pointers.
Some of them prevent copying, so you simply can't copy a unique pointer.
Others keep track of how many people are using the pointer with a reference count.
Not adding a reference count to Person or Employee, but inside the smart pointer there's a reference count,
and so the destructor just decrements the reference count and when it gets to 0, deletes it.
The constructor, obviously, increments the reference count and so does the copy constructor and so does the
assignment operator, and most important of all, operator overloads for a pair of operators you probably
didn't think of were operators, even though I say operator every time I talk about them, star and points to.
The effect of doing this is that you can treat that smart pointer exactly like a pointer except you don't
have to remember to delete it. It's not garbage collection. It's deterministic destruction.
It will get deleted exactly when it goes out of scope or when the last person using the shared_ptr goes
out of scope, but it feels like garbage collection because you're not writing all that code, and it saves you
from having the destructor, the copy constructor, and the assignment operator, the big three, in your class
that have a pointer in it. Oh, they're in the smart pointer, but you don't have to write the smart pointer;
they come with C++ 11. You just get to use them. Watch what happens to our code when we do that.