I love ripping out code. I think every developer loves ripping out code. (Typing)
Less code to test, less code to worry about. I'm going to go into Person
and change this Resource pointer (Typing)
to a shared_ptr (Typing) to a Resource.
Now, that's not going to compile as is, obviously.
I've got to put include in here of memory and I need to call it by its full name, (Typing)
std::shared_ptr. Let's talk for a minute about why I chose shared_ptr.
It implements a reference counted sharing, so that when you copy or assign a Person around, the new Person is
pointing to the same Resource as the old Person. I don't know, let's say it was the char and you changed
some aspect of the char. Everybody, all the Person objects that were copied from each other, they would all
now still be pointing to the same changed Resource. The old semantics that we implemented by hand were that
each Person had their own individual copy of the Resource. I don't think there was necessarily a business
reason for it; it was just, how else were you going to do it?
We weren't about to implement reference counting inside person.
In many cases, a reference counted shared_ptr is a really good way to deal with copying.
If people are making copies of a policy or an employee record or whatever, it should still be
referring to the same other things that it needs to refer to, and as long as one of those copies is still in
scope we shouldn't be deleting the stuff out on the free store.
So I'm going to use a shared_ptr to Resource here inside Person.
Here's the fun part. I don't need the copy constructor anymore. (Typing)
A copy that copies the shared_ptr to Resource in one Person into the shared_ptr to Resource in
another is just fine. The reference count will get incremented.
The sharing will happen. I do not need to write this code, so I can get rid of my copy constructor. (Typing)
Similarly, I can get rid of my operator=. (Typing) When the assignment happens and it just lands on the old
pResource, that's fine. It will do the right thing, send things out of scope if they need to go out of scope,
(Typing) so I can get rid of my operator=. Here, where I'm initializing it's a nullptr --
remember how strings just initialize themselves to "" and you don't need to remember to do it?
Shared_ptr's initialize themselves to empty, so I don't need to initialize pResource, another thing not to
worry about, and I sure as heck don't need to delete it in the destructor.
When Person's destructor goes off all of its member variables will be cleaned away, the strings,
arbitrarynumber, all of them, including the shared_ptr, and the shared_ptr's destructor will go off
and the shared_ptr's destructor, assuming that this is the last person who cares about this particular
Resource, will delete the memory out on the free store. I don't even need to have a destructor. (Typing)
I told you. Love ripping out code. (Typing) Now in AddResource I do need to worry about the old one.
If there was one already I need to tell it, the shared_ptr, to let go of that Resource, and I do that
instead of using delete like this. The error message, by the way, is -- you can't delete that; it's not a
pointer, and it's true. Despite the fact its name starts with p, it's a solid object whose type is what we
call a smart pointer, and it has a member function called reset. (Typing)
Resetting a shared_ptr has it let go of its hold on something out on the free store.
It decrements the reference count and if that takes the reference count to 0, it will delete it --
all done behind the scenes for you, not your problem. Now, you can't initialize a shared_ptr by just
passing it something that you got from new, like this with the equals sign.
The best way to get a value into this shared_ptr is to use the make_shared.
It's again a C++ 11, all of this is C++ 11. Visual C++ 2010 supports the C++ 11 language changes.
So here I'm going to use the make_shared function. It's a templated function and I need to tell it,
I need you to make me a Resource, and then I just pass along the arguments to be given to the constructor
and make_shared will take those arguments, give them to constructor for Resource, get itself a pointer,
put in the member variable, do all the right things, and this smart pointer will be smart.
I've made Person a lot simpler. I ripped out all that code that just took me so long to put in and that was
knowing what I'm doing, but what is going to happen when I run this diabolical main that's running around
copying things and calling AddResource twice, and so on? Let's find out. (Typing)
It's all good. I have two constructs, two destructs, and I'm not making endless copies of the same Resource
for each individual copy of the person. There's a lot of Persons being constructed that you're not seeing
and they're all sharing the same Resource and only when the last one goes out of scope then the Resource is
destructed. No memory leak, no blowing up,
no rule of three because you don't have a raw pointer in Person
anymore, you have a smart pointer in Person and, as you can see, smart developers use smart pointers.