I showed you in the demo how switching a raw pointer to a shared_ptr from the Standard Library just makes
all that work of the big three evaporate and this is how it should be.
There are three important smart pointers in C++ 11. Shared_ptr, which, as I've mentioned, is a reference
counted, non-intrusive, smart pointer, behaves well in collections, does everything you think it should do,
really doesn't have flaws. Weak_ptr, which sort of works with shared_ptr.
Every time you create a copy of a shared_ptr you bump the reference count.
Sometimes you want to have a weak_ptr, which doesn't bump the reference count; its existence doesn't
keep the object alive; and it's possible that the weak_ptr may become empty if the object goes away while the
weak_ptr's still pointing to it, and it handles that really nicely.
There's also unique_ptr, which can't be copied, and there's an algorithm available in the Standard Library
called move that you can use to move values in and out of unique-ptrs.
I should also probably mention auto_ptr, a previous attempt at a smart pointer that was in the Standard
Library. Auto_ptr wasn't as smart as it should be and it worked really poorly in containers, so if you
made a vector or some other standard collection of employee objects, solid objects, that'd work great or you
could make one of raw employee pointers and it would work, but you'd have to delete all of the individual
employees when you deleted the collection. If you put smart pointer auto_ptr into that collection
extraordinarily bad things happened. Shared_ptr and unique_ptr don't have that problem; they work well in
containers; auto_ptr does not. You should be using Visual Studio 2010 or Visual C++ 2010 Express.
They have shared_ptr and unique_ptr. You, therefore, have no need in your life for auto_ptr.
In fact, if you find an auto_ptr in old code that you're maintaining, you should give serious thought to
replacing it because it's flawed in some important ways. Don't use auto_ptr when you're writing new code.
Use shared_ptr or unique_ptr; they're the way to go from here forward.