I showed you how much simpler using a shared_ptr is, but perhaps you need to be convinced that it's actually
usable as a pointer. Back in the copy constructor and the assignment operator we had some calls to
Resource's GetName function,
which you see here, and if you remember what those calls look like it was just
pResource, arrow, GetName. Let's come up with an excuse to call that from some other member function, a
Person, having now deleted most of the member functions of Person that were managing Resource, so that you
can see how easy it is still to use the pointer. Let's come here into Person and add a function called
GetResourceName. The ResourceName's of strings, a GetResourceName, (Typing) doesn't take any parameters,
doesn't change the object, (Typing) and it'll just return (Typing) that pResource, (Typing) points to, and
you see I even get IntelliSense. pResource is the shared_ptr. It's not any kind of a pointer with a star
and yet, because of the overload the operator points to, I can call the methods just as though it was a
traditional raw pointer, so I can call pResource, GetName. (Typing)
And now I've implemented GetResourceName. Back in here, if I want
to I can take any one of these Persons and just declare another string. (Typing)
They could be on one line, but let's do it down here.
String s1 is equal to, say (Typing) Kate.GetResourceName
(Typing) and we've implemented that function so that's going to work just fine and we'll be able to bring the
Resource by calling GetResourceName,
which is going to use the smart pointer pResource just as though it was a traditional raw pointer.
One of the great things about this is that you can take code that was written using raw pointers, which is
full of these arrow operators and so on, and just go and make this change, so that you declare to be a
shared_ptr instead of a raw pointer,
and then here use make_shared instead of =new and that, in very many cases, that, and ripping out all the
deletes, is all that you have to do to switch over to a shared_ptr.
Once you've made the switch you can forget that it's a shared_ptr and just treat it as though it was a raw
pointer everywhere in your application. Dereferencing it with star where that's appropriate and by using
this points to operator. Simple as that.