Here's some sample
code that just plays around with pointers and I have to tell you that this demo suffers from the same
problem that all first pointer demos suffer from, which that it is utterly pointless and I'm just going to
confess that to you. I'm going to show you the mechanics and the syntax of how to get pointers and how to
use them, but you would never do this. You have a perfectly good integer A; you would just work with A.
Why would you make a pointer to it and then go through the pointer?
Where pointers become useful is when, for example, you pass them down to a function or you keep them in a
member variable and then you use them again later. Then, knowing how to go through the pointer to get what
you want back from the original fundamental type or the original object is a useful thing to know.
That sets up a lot of complexity for our first demo, so we do it all together.
Hopefully this is pretty straightforward. I make myself an integer called A, print out its value, make a
pointer to that very same integer by using the address of operator, and then I use the pointer, *pA, to
change the value that the pointer points to, to 4. Since the pointer points to A, this also changes A's
value to 4. There's only one piece of memory. You can just talk to it two ways, you can call it A or you
can call it *pA. And I make a different integer and now I change my pointer, pA,
to actually point to b and of course its name means nothing right?
So, it's called pA, but now it points to b.
If I take the contents of pA and do a ++ operator on them, b will be incremented from 100 to 101.
Here when we print out the contents of pA it's going to print out 101.
It works with objects too, so here I make a Person called Kate and a Person pointer called pKate is equal to
the address of that object Kate. And then this is kind of the long way, I can say the contents of pKate,
wrap that in brackets and then dot SetNumber. And as you can see the compiler,
I've got no error messages here.
It knows that that is a Person function, but I can also use the arrow notation.
So here where I'm using a solid object Kate, I use the dot notation.
And here where I'm using the pointer pKate I use the arrow notation, pKate points to GetName.
The same thing's going on over here with number.
Then we have some references, integer reference rA. Now, unlike a pointer, you can't just say, oh I have
this integer reference and I'll tell you later what it points to.
You have to say, is equal to, in this case, a. Then if I change rA to 5 that will actually change a to 5
because rA is just an alias now for a. You saw this when variables were passed down to functions.
The parameters were passed by reference, that when you changed the local variable inside the function
it actually changed the value of the parameter back in the calling code that had been passed down by reference.
That's what reference means, that you can kind of change another place, talking to it with this different
name. You can have references to objects as well as to people, so here I make a Person reference to that
same Kate object and call its SetNumber and then I can call its GetName and notice because it's a reference
that I'm using dot notation both for the gets and for the sets, for all the member functions, which for many
people is more readable than the pointer notation. Let's quickly run this just to prove that everything
does what you think it will do.
a is 3.
Let's just line these up. a is 3. When we make the pointer pA and then change its contents to 4, a becomes
4. We make the pointer pA now actually point to b and then we increment it.
When we print it out pA becomes 100 that then got incremented to 101,
so it's not touching a anymore it's only now touching b because that's where the pointer points.
With the objects we have a 234 from my arbitrarynumber and then using the pointer we change it to 235, print
it out both ways. We get 235 both ways because they're again, the same piece of memory,
no matter how you talk to them.
When we set rA to be a and then change rA to 5 and then print out a,
a is now 5 because rA is just an alias for a, and similarly
when we make rKate to Kate and then set its number to 345, print it out, it prints out 345.
I have code here that's commented out and let's kind of go through and talk about how the compiler would help
me if I absent-mindedly wrote this code. Here, I declare a pointer, and it's sort of foreshadowing that it
has the name badPointer, and I don't set it to the address of anything.
I just say, la la la, it's an integer badPointer and then I try to use it.
I try to go through badPointer and put 3 in there. Also, down here I try to go through badPointer and get
the value to print it out. If I run this (Typing)
a bad thing happens and, specifically, the variable badPointer is being used without being initialized, so
we'll just
put that to stop.
I told you that when I read the code, but you also noticed that it sort of blows up when the application runs
and that's a really bad plan. I can make this a little better if I initialize my badPointer to nullptr.
It's a C++ 11 feature if you're not using Visual Studio 2010 you can't use nullptr, but Visual C++ 2010
Express understands this C++ 11 feature, so it's all set. Now, if I just make only this change and run it
things don't really get much better. After all, it still doesn't point anywhere right?
We do still unfortunately go boom, but you notice we're going boom in a nicer way?
It's actually possible that we could send an error report, I'm not going to, and that this might be
a less severe situation. In fact, here we throw a nullptr exception that I could handle.
We haven't done exceptions yet, so I'm not going to dwell on that.
What's really important about initializing your pointer to nullptr is that you can test for nullptr very
compactly. So I can come here and say if badPointer (Typing), I'll use it, otherwise, I won't.
If I run this code (Typing)
we don't blowup.
The if kept me out of this block and prevented me from trying to dereference, that's what this process is
called, preventing me from trying to dereference the bad pointer.
Now, you might think well, it was just the if that helped you out, so let's take the equals nullptr back away
and run it again (Typing).
We're back to the very bad thing. Setting it to nullptr is what enables me to test whether, in fact, it's a
nullptr or not. When a pointer has the value nullptr or nullptr, as some people like to pronounce it,
this if will return false and we'll be protected. When it has random bits that happened to be in that
location before, it won't be protected. Any nonzero number comes out as true, so the if badPointer will say,
oh yeah, we're good, and it will go in here and try to dereference the pointer and then your program will blow up.
If you're going to use a pointer you need to be sure that it was initialized.
One way to be sure is to declare them and immediately give them a value, as you saw right here, but another
way is to declare them and immediately give them the value nullptr and then always check to see if they're
nullptr or not before you use them. Let's uncomment some badReference code now (Typing).
Pretty much the same thing, but an important difference. There's red wigglies right here.
There wasn't here. (Typing) Compiler's fine with you just declaring pointers and not initializing them to
anything. Let's put that back before I forget. It's not fine with you declaring a reference and not
initializing it to anything, so you can't make this mistake and there's no way to test, is this a null
reference because there's no such thing as a null reference. References have to be initialized pointing to
something real and that's one of the ways that they are simpler because you can't, oh I have to initialize,
I have to check if it's null yet. It's not optional. It will be initialized.
It won't be null. You will be able to use it. That's also, sometimes, the reason why you can't use
references because sometimes, you know, things are optional and you don't know if they're set or not.
When you can use references I prefer to use them; they're simpler.
You can use the dot notation instead of the arrow and you don't have to check to see if they're null or not,
but that's exactly why you also sometimes can't use them.