Const is a C++ keyword and as the keyword it's spelled with a lowercase c.
It means that you promise you won't change a value. That might be because you simply want to impose a little
rigor on yourself or it might be that you're being given a value that you're not allowed to change and you
have to promise that you won't. You can declare a local variable like this, const int zero = 0, and any code
that tries to set 0 to 10 or -3 will trigger a compiler error. It's not allowed to be changed.
You can take a function, foo here can take a const int i. That's a semi-pointless thing to do, right,
because i here is being passed by value and any changes you make you'll only be changing inside foo
and who cares because they'll be thrown away when foo goes out of scope.
But the second line, something takes a const Person reference p and we've said a couple times,
when you pass something by reference someone can reach through the reference and change the
value back in the call in code. Taking a const reference says, actually I won't.
It means, I'm taking this by reference because the cost of a copy might be expensive.
You know, when you take a function parameter by value, that integer or that person or that insurance policy
or whatever, is copied into a temporary that's given to the function and that may be
a very expensive copy. Passing by reference prevents the copy, but it enables someone to change the real
object back in the call in code and if you don't want that then you write const person reference p.
What will happen now is when the compiler compiles something, if any code in it changes p you'll get a
compiler error, so it's a very safe way to say, I'm giving you a reference to spare the copy, but this
doesn't mean that you can actually make changes back in my code.
Imagine that I take that Person p as a const reference and I call some member function on it like GetName or
GetNumber. Unless the compiler knows that those member functions don't change any of the member variables of
person it won't allow you to make the function call. You have to give it that reassurance and you do that
this way. This says that the GetName function won't change any of the member variables of the class.
That makes them safe to call on a const reference. If we have a const Person or a const Person reference or
whatever called p and we want to call p.GetName. That's safe to do as long as the compiler knows
that GetName is a const function. It won't change any of the member variables of p.
As you can imagine, getting all your consts lined up can be a challenge.
It's called const correctness, so if our function something takes a const Person reference and the code for
something calls p.GetName, GetName has to be const. Well GetName's really simple.
You've met Person in lots of these demos. You know that all it does is return the first name and the last
name tag together, but what if it called another member function?
Well than that member function would have to have const on it and some of the functions may take parameters
that need to be labeled as const whatever reference to make sure they're not getting changed.
If you leave const correctness till the end of your development it can just drive you crazy, but if you do it
as you're writing it can actually be a supportive framework that helps you to write higher quality code.