Here I have an ordinary console application and I'm using the Person class once again, and I've also declared
a little function here up above the main. Let's take a look at what the main does --
starts really simple. I make a local integer called i, then I make a constant integer called ci.
They both happen to have the same value in them.
I'm allowed to change the value of i, but if I try to change the value of ci I get wigglies.
Error. Expression must be a modifiable lvalue.
Const variables aren't modifiable, so modifying them gets you an error message.
Let's take a look at this function DoubleIt. Right now it takes its parameter by value.
Let's change it so that it takes it's parameter by reference. This causes an error here.
Why? Because 10 is not modifiable. If I have code in here that I don't know, makes x 4, that's allowed
and it would change what was passed to it, so here when we called it with j it would change j and in here it
would try to change the 10, which is just weird. Now, there's no particular reason to take an integer by
Reference. The cost of copying an integer is not important,
but many people are in the habit of taking things by reference, just, it's a habit and they do it.
When you take something by reference then you should try to take it by const reference.
Now making that change makes this line happy, but now you notice it's made this
line unhappy and this unhappiness here is, well, what are you doing?
It must be modifiable, right? Because once you've said it's a const reference you can't change it.
Let's take that away. Now we have, generally, a happy compiler.
Any time you're going to write a function that takes something by reference and you might pass a literal,
like 10, to it it needs to take it by a const reference, and that's what you saw in the template.
We had const t ref. We take those things by reference because operators should take their parameters by
reference for a variety of reasons and if you're going to pass literal constants like 33 and 44
then it has to be a const reference.
Now I've got some code that's going to work with objects. I have a Person object called Kate, and I can call
SetNumber on that, and then I have a const Person called cKate and I have some commented out code that's
going to try to talk to it. Let's uncomment this one, (Typing) trying to call SetNumber, and see I get an
error message, and it's not quite as good as the error message when you were trying to change the value of
the constant int, but the object has type qualifiers that are not compatible with the member function.
It's a constant; I'm trying to set its number; that's a bad thing.
You know what, if I uncomment this line I also get an error here.
Same thing: type qualifiers that are not compatible with the member function.
We look at GetNumber and we're like, that doesn't change any member variables.
Let's take a look at the definition of it.
It just returns number. It doesn't change anything.
How could this possibly be a problem? Well here's the deal.
When the compiler has this line to process it doesn't go and look at all the code for GetNumber.
In fact, it doesn't have access to all the code for GetNumber in some cases.
Right?, that may be off in some cpp. For the particular case of Person the code is
inline in the header file, but you can't count on that, and even if it was available, it's not a good use of
the compiler's time to be rooting through your code to look and see if it changes any member variables.
Instead, the way that you say this function doesn't change any member variables is you put the word const in
your declaration. Now notice, if I put const here I have to build in order to get my header file parsed, but
I get errors. (Typing)
Specifically here, arbitrarynumber cannot be modified because it is being accessed through a const object.
By saying its SetNumber was const now my code won't compile because you know what,
SetNumber's not a const function of Person. It changes a member variable of person.
Compiler won't let you lie here, so take that away. The compiler will let me say that GetNumber is const.
Well, it will also let me say that GetName is const and when you have something declared in the cpp
you need to put the const in both places
here. Now GetName is const because I put it in both places.
GetNumber's only in the header, so I only need to put it there.
SetNumber isn't const. It changes member variables of Person.
If you look down the rest of these operators you can probably also put some const correctness in here
relatively simply. You know that the operator&lt; doesn't change the Person
that you're comparing to and doesn't change this person either.
This is not by reference, so it's harmless, but we'll put that it doesn't change this.
And the friend, the free function, can't have a const modifier out here because it's a free function.
It doesn't have access to member variables of Person, but I can say that it takes a const ref.
Then, for those that are
implemented here in the cpp, while they don't match I'll get warnings
saying, uh I don't know why you're telling me about the operator&lt; that takes a Person reference.
As far as I know you don't have one of those. It's true. I only have an operator&lt; the text of const Person
reference. I also need to add this here that it doesn't change it, any of the member variables of the class,
and here. And this isn't a member function, so I wouldn't put the const out on the end there.
I have red wigglies here. They tell me that I'm not allowed to access arbitrarynumber.
It's a little confusing because, didn't we make it a friend?
No, we made this one a friend. (Typing) Now that one's a friend.
If you think, as you go to write the function, do I change the things I'm passed
if I'm taking them by reference? Immediately put that const in there.
You don't have to go through this process of fixing it up afterwards.
Let's go back now. Notice we have red wigglies underneath call to SetNumber, but not to GetNumber, and
that's really what you would expect. GetNumber doesn't change the person; it's a perfectly safe thing to
call on a const Person. SetNumber does, and no amount of adding the word const is going to fix that.
In fact, when we tried making SetNumber a const function it failed.