You can use the const keyword when you're declaring pointers too and it has two different possible meanings.
First, you can declare that the pointer is a constant pointer. This means it can't be changed to point
somewhere else, so in the first pointer demo the pA pointer suddenly started pointing at B instead.
A constant pointer can't. Or, you can say that it's pointing to something const.
Then *cpI is const and you can't say *cpI = 7. You can't use the pointer to change the value of that const
integer. As you can imagine, if you take the address of a const integer, you better put it in a const
integer pointer saying I'm pointing to something const. Course, you could do both if you want.
This syntax declares a pointer that you cannot change to point somewhere else and nor can you go through the
pointer to change the value of what it's pointing at. I've called it crazy because it sounds like there'd be
nothing for it, but you can use it to get values and to invoke const functions, which may be enough for you.