I'll just quickly show you the error messages that you get when you declare constant pointers or pointers to
constant things and then break your own rules.
Here, I have some code that works with the const and non-const objects that we already have kicking around.
This is an integer pointer pI that's the address of i, no problem, but if I uncomment this line, if I try
to take the address of that const i, a value of type const integer pointer can't be in use to initialize an
entity of type integer pointer. In other words, if I want to do that, get that address of cI, I have to put
it in a const integer pointer. Here, I'm going to make a Person pointer, address of this Person up here.
That's fine. And another local Person, and then I'm going to try to make some pointers.
So if I make a const integer pointer, that is a pointer to a const int called pcI,
I can point that to the same place that this pI is pointing.
In other words, the same non-const I under the covers, but because I've said that it's a pointer to a const,
if I then try to go through it and do things, expression must be a modifiable lvalue.
The compiler doesn't try to follow back the chain and so on. I said pcI was a pointer to a const, then I
tried to use it to change the value. What am I doing? And I get an error message.
Notice, however, that I can change the pointer itself, pcI, to now point to a completely different local
variable,
j, that's sitting up here and is a non-const integer. Can take the address of that, put it in pcI,
not a problem. I'm allowed to change where the pointer points to.
Here the word const has moved away from the type and closer to the pointer.
This is a constant pointer, so I can use it, *cpI, reach out through the contents and change where it points
to the value 4, which means that i, among other things is going to change to 4.
But this line of code that tries to get it to point to j instead: (Typing) expression must be a modifiable lvalue.
I'm not allowed to change the value of cpI, not the value that it --- want to store through it when I go
*cpI, but the actual value in cpI, the address, not allowed to change it.
Now here's this crazy one, constant pointer to a constant int and I can't do either of these things, so I
(Typing) can't reach out through the pointer, must be a modifiable lvalue, and can't try to get it to point
somewhere else. (Typing) I can use it. I can say int k is equal to the contents of crazy (Typing), so it's
not completely worthless I just can't change either where it's pointing to or the value contained in what
it's pointing to and that's the story of const and pointers.