So far, the only variables you've seen in all of these little sample applications have been local variables,
what we sometimes call, being on the stack and having stack semantics.
They go out of scope when the function ends and in fact, they go out of scope when they hit a brace bracket,
so if you have an if and then you declare some integer i inside the brace brackets of the if, do some
calculations, then you hit the close brace bracket of the if, the i actually goes out of scope.
That's not always what you want. Sometimes you actually want variables that have a longer life than that and
in C++ those variables live in what we call the free store. A small aside, many people use the word stack
for local variables and heap for the free store and if you go to a computer science textbook and look them up
stack and heap are data structures. They're ways of keeping information.
With stack you push things on and pop them off and the heap is a way to keep a large quantity of data and be
able to get to it when you want to. The technical terms, local variables or automatic storage, and the free
store. I say heap a lot, meaning the free store, so do an awful lot of C++ developers.
It's actually the leftover C name and many times the free store is implemented as a heap.
It's not exactly wrong to use local and stack interchangeably, to use free store and heap interchangeably.
It's a very common pattern among developers you're going to talk to.
You may even meet a few guys who say, huh, free store? What's that? and you'll say, the heap and they'll
say, oh, why didn't you say so. You may run into sticklers who say, what do you mean the heap?
I believe you will find it's the free store. You're like, okay,
so I'm telling you both names and technically the accurate name is the free store.
That said, most developers say heap. Anyway, it's for longer-lived variables and there's an operator called
new that sets aside some memory for you in the free store and this operator returns a pointer to what has
just been created for you up in the free store, the instance of a class, the object.
It also calls the constructor for you, so it creates the object completely:
sets aside the memory, sets aside the memory, runs its constructor.
What you get back is a pointer to a fully-constructed, happy, ready-to-go object.
It will stay on the free store forever until you decide you don't want it anymore and then you call delete on
that pointer that you got back from new and, among other things, the destructor will run to clean up anything
that the object has a hold of and the memory will be released back to the free store to be used for other
requests to new up an object. If you were creating what we call a raw array, if you want 100 integers you
want the memory for 100 integers continuously on the free store, the syntax is a little different for both
the new and the delete. However, beginners should stay away from raw arrays and instead use collections from
the Standard Library that we'll get to later. Using new and using delete are how you manage the lifetime of
the objects that you create up on the free store.