Let's elaborate on this. You create something up on the free store with new and you get given a pointer.
Somebody has to call delete on that pointer to give that memory back to the free store.
In its simplest form you have beginning of a function new employee, do something with employee pointer, at
the end of the function, delete the employee pointer, but that's kind of pointless.
You could've just used a local variable. Why did you bother newing something up?
Probably this pointer is going to go into a member variable of a class and you need to keep track and call
delete when everybody's done, but along the way some strange things can happen like, someone could copy your
pointer and maybe they still have the copy when you think you're done with the original pointer.
If you delete the pointer, the copy they have is pointing to memory that's not available for use.
That's a blow-up-your-application situation or if you keep your pointer in some local variable that goes
out of scope and you don't have the pointer anymore to call delete with.
Manual memory management is flat-out hard. You can delete things too soon and then other code tries to use
them and they're not there. You can delete twice and you can never delete, which is a memory leak.
It's actually quite difficult. The good news is you almost never have to do it.
Library writers have solved this problem for you, but to convince you that you want to use what the library
writers have written I'm going to show you how to do it yourself by hand so that you know what you're being
saved and so that you maybe understand where some of the eye rolling and stories have come from, from people
who say, oh my gosh, C++ pointers, new, delete, memory leaks. You have to do it yourself by hand.
I'll show you what they're talking about, but the whole time I'm doing it I want you to remember you
probably don't have to do this. Okay? I'm going to teach you something called the Rule of Three.
The Rule of Three says, if you write a destructor that really does something bad, because remember delete
doesn't just give the memory back it also runs the destructor, you should also write a Copy Constructor and
a Copy Assignment Operator. I have a demo for you in which we're going to deliberately trigger all kinds of
chaos and mayhem and slowly bring it under control by writing the big three: Copy Constructor, Copy
Assignment Operator, and Destructor.