When you're working with variables in C++, one of things that's just an underpinning of the way the whole thing
works is that every variable has a type and C++ is a strongly typed language.
That means that the type doesn't change over the lifetime of the program.
If x is an integer, it can hold integers and integers only, and something else will have to hold dates or strings,
or other kinds of information. Before you can put a value into a variable you must declare it anywhere before
you use it including even really right on you put a value into it and when you declare it specify its type and
then that's it, that's its type. Why do I say the complier is your friend?
Because in a strongly typed language you can't put a string into a variable that's expecting a number or number
into a variable that's expecting a string and these kinds of errors where you forget to convert things are caught
for you by the complier and it says wait, those things are compatible, what are you doing?
Other times maybe it says you are throwing away some information.
I'll do this but I'm going to have to make a conversion and you'll lose some precision and these warnings often
cause you to realize --- I wasn't thinking, I didn't even want to put that value into that variable, so that's
how the compiler can kind of save you from trouble. Now I'm talking first about fundamental types and by this
I mean types that are built into the language. Things to hold numbers, true or false, and C++ also has a type
called character that can be used to hold either a small number or a single character like the letter a.
There are also user defined types in C++, defined by you personally or by some library that you're using.
In fact, the very first Hello World demo that I showed in this material, we had a string to put someone's name into
you could write your own string if you wanted to, not a lot of value in that, the one that comes with the
standard library is very good, but you could write something that represented an employee, or a bank account, or
an insurance policy, or a nuclear reactor if you liked, and those would be user defined types.
User defined types in C++ can be either structs or classes.
I'm going to talk about those a little later on, not in this module, but you'll see that they are first class citizens
and they can do everything that the fundamental types can do.
That's an important thing that sets C++ apart for some other languages.
So when I'm telling you what can be done for fundamental types, remember that that same suite of possibilities is
also there for types you define or types that are defined in a library that you're using.