The fundamental types can be categorized according to what they hold, what kind of information they hold.
So there are a series of types for example that hold integers, numbers without a fractional part, like 3 or 702
and in C++ we have short, long, int, unsigned short, unsigned long, and unsigned int.
Short and long as you can probably guess from their names, different lengths, they have a different number of
bytes in them. An int is a convenient type that is actually chosen a length to be the most efficient on the machine
where it's running. So if you really don't care about the length at all because you're just going to put a number
in it like 3, int is a great choice. The unsigned versions can each hold a number twice as large as the signed
versions because they don't use a bit for sign. We'll talk more about how many bytes a number can hold and what
happens if you try to put overlarge numbers in, in a little while.
You won't go wrong when you first start by just putting integers into variables of type ints.
It's easy to remember, it's probably right, and unless you happen to be getting near the limit of the number that
can fit into the bytes, you're going to be doing just fine and that's a very large number as you'll see shortly.
Now, if your number has a fractional part, if it's a 7.2, 3.29, then that's a real number and you can use either
float or a double and double has more capacity, can hold larger numbers, and more digits of precision than float can.
Most of the time, just put things in doubles and your life will tick along as you expect.
There's also a type called character and believe or not, C++ people argue about how to say the name of this type.
Some people including me pronounce it char, but you will meet people who call it char.
Take my advice and don't argue about how to pronounce variable types, if someone says char this is what they mean,
if someone says char this is what they mean, you pronounce it however you want.
There's even an unsigned char, which probably doesn't sound like it makes an sense, I means what's -a or for that
matter, how is +y different from -y? Well, because char is a very small number of bytes, only 8 bytes, people
sometimes use it to hold little numbers like 3 and they therefore want to be able to distinguish whether their
putting say -3 in it or a positive number. So char and unsigned char can technically be used for numbers, but
they can also be used to hold a single letter and finally we can round out our fundamental types with Boolean values
true or false and they are of type bool. The only values that you can put into a bool are true or false, but there
are ways to convert to that from other values and one thing you'll especially see when we get into operators is
people converting back and forth from numbers to Boolean, but the only values a bool can hold are true or false.