I have a demo to show you that will take these types out for a spin, show us putting some values back and forth into
different types of variables, and what happens especially when you mix and match types and convert maybe from one
type to another, So here in
Visual C++ Express, I have a project called VariablesAndTypes and you see for example here we declare an integer
called i1 and initialize it with a value of 1 and then I'm printing the values out onto the console output and
that's why I have this include here of iostream so that I can use standard console output to write to.
I declare another integer here and don't give if a value right away, but then give it a value on the next line,
and there's really no important difference between these two, for integers.
There can be a difference for your own user defined types, I'll talk about that in a little while and then this
third way which some people ask about when the first time they see it.
Actually initializing that integer using these round brackets and this is another way to do.
It's simply a matter of taste. These three have no real difference.
If I run this application with Ctrl+F5, let it compile
and then I'll just pull this window down so that you can see the code, hopefully no one is terribly surprised that
i1 comes out as 1, i2 as 2, and i3 as 3 because those are the values that I've initialized them to.
If we scroll down a little further in the code, you can see we've got a couple of doubles here.
I'm putting a real number into d1 2.2 and for d2 I'm assigning to the value that's in i1.
So i1's an integer and the integers we say promoted to a double and there's no loss of any information, that's just fine.
But this next line, we take another integer i4 and we assign it to this value that's in d1, which is 2.2.
Now you can't put 2.2 into an integer, so we're going to lose some information.
If you're expecting a runtime error from doing this, you don't get one. Let's take a look at the output
obviously there's no error messages, d1 comes out as 2.2, d2 comes out as 1, which is what was in i1 and i4 comes
out as 2, the value is just truncated silently it runtime with no complaints and if that was what you wanted, fantastic,
if it wasn't there was a way to find out that you were going to have this problem, but it's not something you'll
be told about at runtime.
Let's carry down here. I have a character called c1 and you see that it's perfectly ordinary to put a value into
a character using single quotes then the letter then end single quote.
I have a line here that's currently commented out that uses double quotes, I'm going to let you see the error
message from that in a moment, we'll print out c1
and not surprisingly it's a
and then I have some Boolean values, I call it flag and I started as false, print that out.
It actually prints out 0 when you send the Boolean value to c out.
Then I take that and I assign it to i1, which you remember had the numerical value of 1
and sure enough it comes out as 1. It sounds like you can put a number into a
bool so just to prove you can, I'm going to take this double number, d1, which has the value
2.2, put it into the flag and it still prints out 1 because really what flag is, is true and when you send true to
console output, it happens to put a 1 on the screen, but its value is either true or false and the easiest way to
see that is if I rerun the application under the debugger.
So I'm going to Stop this run
and just before you do the debugger run, I'll show you what would happen if I were to try to compile this line
that's trying to initialize a character using double quotes rather than single quotes.
To a lot of people from other programming languages, when they see "b", the think we'll that's a single character,
but it's not. It's what a lot of people call c style string, it's actually an array of characters with a special
termination character at the end of the array. So one real character the letter b and the special
termination character. We're not using those kinds of strings because I think the standard strings are much easier
to work with, but I just want you to know that you can't initialize a character using a string.
So you can see there's red wiggles here and it says Error: a value of type "const char*" cannot be used to initialize
an entity of type "char". The important part of that is probably the word error.
When you want to initialize a character use only a single quote, a single quote for a single character, easy way
to remember it. So let's comment that back out and this time I'm going to run the application under the debugger
because I want to show you how the debugger displays Boolean values.
Now this, exact ins and outs of how to debug an application are not what we're here for, so I'm just going to treat
the debugger as a way to let you see values. The way to see values is to pause the program and you pause at what's
called a break point. Lots of ways to get break points in your application.
If you're not familiar with Visual Studio probably your best choice is to simply right click on a line, Breakpoint,
Insert Breakpoint. Once you're a little bit more familiar, you'll recognize this gray margin as sort of the
breakpoint margin and you can click on one to make it go away, or click on the empty margin to set one, but if
you're not 100% which margins are which, right click to set your breakpoints.
Now when I hit this,
we will run
just up until the breakpoint and then we'll stop. Now here, stopped at the breakpoint, you can see this window
here called Autos. If for some reason you don't see this window when you're doing this yourself, you can go on the
Debug menu, choose Windows, and bring up a particular window that you might want.
Locals is a perfectly good substitute for Autos, it simply shows a few more values.
Now you can see here that paused execution before we're running this line.
The i1 value is just gibberish. In fact, what the debugger is showing is just what happened to used to be in that
memory, we haven't yet declared the variable or put a value into it.
So if I step over this line, using this Step Over button on the toolbar, now you can see down here that i1 has
the value 1. Now none of this is terribly exciting because you watched all these in the console window and they
probably weren't that exciting the first time through. So I'm just going to scroll down to here, right click,
and choose Run To Cursor, just to whiz past all of that.
Because what I actually think is worth seeing is the way the debugger displays our Boolean value of flag.
So when I step over this line, and let's look around and find flag, it has the value false and you see that the
debugger doesn't show 0 the way the console output did, but it actually shows false, which is much more helpful
for you to understand what's going on and when we set flag = to i1 which has a numerical value of 1, now the debugger
reports that as true, and when we set flag = to d1, which has a numerical value of 2.2, you can see that the debugger
continues to report that as true. So using the debugger can sometimes give a little more insight into what's
going on and how your data is being interpreted. The console out writing isn't always quite as useful as the debugger.
To kind of illustrate that a little more firmly, I'm going to uncomment some code that I've had hidden and this is
some code working with characters, but putting numbers into that character type.
The reason I'm doing this with character is because it's small enough that we can all kind of know what it can hold.
An unsigned character hold 8 bytes, as signed character holds 7 bytes of number and 7 bytes is a number up to 127
and 8 bytes is a number up to 255. Now, just before I uncomment this code, I want you to see that it uses the
sytle of C++ comments. So you've already seen a single pair of // on a line to makes the whole rest of the line
into a comment, the /* character signifies the beginning of a comment, which can be only even part of a line if
you want or many lines, as this one is, and the */ indicates the end of that comment.
So if I delete the beginning and the end of the comment, now this code is incorporated into my application again
and I'll compile it. I'm using the keystroke Ctrl+Shift+B to Build.
You can also just come up here to the Solution, right click, and choose Build Solution.
So what we're doing, I mentioned an unsigned character can hold up to 255, so I'm going to put 128 in there, that's fine.
We're also going to make a character which can hold up to 127 and try to put a 128 into it and see what debugger
has to say about that. SO let's put a breakpoint here, and run to here.
It hits the first breakpoint, I'm just going to hit Run again to run down to the second one and we'll Step through.
So you can see that n1 has the numerical value 128 and this is the character that that represents.
We don't really care about it as a character we're using it for numbers and n2 is showing that it holds the number
-128, that's because of the way that numbers are represented in terms of bytes and the bit pattern when you try to
put 128 into something that can't hold it, ends up being interpreted as the largest negative number it can hold.
So when we put those onto the output, that's what it's going to print out and that can be really confusing.
If we try even bigger numbers, say 254, which is about as much as n1 can hold, and n1 successfully reports back
254, again that's a very strange character, but n2 thinks that -2 and finally if we take a number that's too large
for both of them like 300, they both say 44. Here's n2 saying 44 and down here you see n1 saying 44.
You notice there were no warnings, no exceptions, nothing at runtime to tell us that this was a bad thing and
that really brings me back to what I said before about the complier is your friend.
So let's let this application run back out and I'm going to compile the application once again.
So Rebuild the Solution. Normally the complier's pretty smart, it only builds things that have changed.
When you choose Rebuild, it rebuilds everything whether it needs to or not and for the first time, I'm going to show
you my build Output. What we have here in the Output is a whole pile of warning messages, they're not errors.
The compile succeeds, the application can run, but they are all warnings from the compiler, from your
friend the complier and it's saying, look you're converting, let's double click these to go to the lines, you're
converting that double 2.2 and putting it in an integer, possible loss of data, yes indeed.
Here, you're forcing integer value into a Boolean value and among other things that's a performance warning and of
course, if you actually planned to keep the number around as a number, you've lost it, all you know is true or
false at that point. Here, this warning, I'm going to truncate your 128, it won't fit in here and it goes onto
continue to warn you about truncations all the time that I'm messing around with our character number.
Now although you wouldn't really put outsize numbers into characters, you might accidently put outsize numbers
into shorts and longs and I don't expect anyone to memorize how long these things can how, I'll show you how to
find that out in just a moment, but the important thing to know is that the compiler knows how long they can hold.
So that especially when you're working directly with constants, it can tell you, this data type cannot hold the
number 128, you've chosen the wrong data type if 128 is what you need to put into it and that's one of the services
the compiler can offer to you, as well if you take two doubles regardless of their values and multiple them together
and try to put the answer into an integer. Even though they're not constants at compile time like 2.2, the complier
still knows you're probably going to lose data when you take that double and put it into an integer and it will
warn you about it. In many ways, the moral of the story is don't ignore your complier warning messages, read
them, they are trying to help you. Now I promised I'd show you how to get the value that a certain type can hold.
How big a number can you put in a char? How big a number can you put in an int and so on?
If you go into MSDN and you find this page Fundamental Types, you can navigate to it what you can see based on
here on the screen of this tree or you could just search for it.
Then you'll find the different types in C++ along with some specific extra types that Visual C++ defines.
For the best cross platform experience, you want to stick with the ones that are actually built in C++ types.
So you can see here the definition of char, bool, short, int, an so on and talking a little bit about how long
they are, however, I find that the best thing to figure out their length is to come down here to this chart and
you can see that it takes up a byte of memory or 2 bytes of memory, or 8 bytes of memory or so on and as well,
if you scroll right down to the bottom, you'll see this link here to Data Type Ranges,
Here, it shows you the range that each type can hold. So int is 4 bytes, it can hold -2 billion to +2 billion
and change. Char as I mentioned can hold -128 to 127, whereas unsigned char can hold 0 to 255 and so on.
So if want to know what maximum and minimum numbers you can put into a particular data type, this is the place to
come and look. As I say, if you're just generally working with small numbers, you might be able to get away with
char, but 255 and 127 are not that big, so just go with int and generally speaking, unless you're writing an operating
system, you're going to be fine and that's my advice to most people.
Put integers into IntelliSense, put real numbers into doubles, and don't spend too much time worrying about what
exactly what size and how many bytes the various types are until it matters it to you and when you're just getting
started, it doesn't matter yet, but you have seen the types that we have in C++ now and a little bit of what happens
as you move the data back and forth from one type to another.