In the demo that we just went through, you saw data moving back and forth between say integers and doubles, doubles
and integers, integers and Booleans, characters back and forth around from type to type.
Yes we wrapped up with an overflow, but not all types conversions involved overflows, or loss of data, or
are somehow bad. In fact, taking data in a variable of one type and putting it in another type is a very common
thing to do in C++ and the complier will take care of the conversion if the types are compatible.
Sometimes it will just have nothing to say about the whole process.
You have an integer you want to put it in a double, no big deal, we'll promote the integer value to a double value
and put that new promoted double value into your variable.
If what you're doing could cause a loss of data, the complier will give you a warning.
If the types are completely incompatible like a double quoted string trying to be put into a character, then the
complier will give you an error and the application won't run.
Once you have it complied and all you have is warnings, you're not going to get runtime errors as you move things
around from one type or another. That stuff is taken care of at compile time and there are not checks at runtime
that's a performance feature. Now this means that you mustn't ignore compiler warnings.
Some compiler warnings are telling you about serious possible bugs like throwing away all of the decimal places
in your floating point number when you put it into an integer.
The problem is if you have a large project, you have normally 307 warnings, you might not notice that this morning
you have 308 warnings and you really need to go and look at the new one because it's a bug waiting to happen.
The solution to this of course is don't have 307 warnings.
There's a mechanism called casting that lets you tell the complier, I know what I'm doing here, this is my choice,
I know I don't have an integer, but you want you to turn it into an integer and then put that newly made integer
into my variable. Then they'll be no more warning and it's clear to anyone who's reading your code, what it is
you're trying to do. Now, can this be dangerous? Of course it can, if that's a double with points of information
in it that you needed to keep and you cast it to an integer and throw them away, nobody's going to stop you.
C++ the saying goes, makes it easy to shoot your foot off, and the compiler when you cast, basically says well okay
it's your foot, you know you're asserting that you know what you're doing, I'm going to believe that you know
what you're doing. These traditional casts, which are sometimes called c style casts are not the absolute best
practice, after we've gone through templates in this material, I can show you some safer and better casts, but for
now, I'm going to go through traditional C style casts, which basically tell the compiler, back off, I know
what I'm doing and while we're talking about converting types back and forth, I also want to show you the suffixes
that you'll occasionally see on numbers and their only allowed on numbers to indicate the type of a literal.
So a literal is a number like 0 or 1, or 2.2 and these suffixes can say, I'm telling you that this is a long or
I'm telling you that this is a float and that's done as a form of casting to say, I would like to take a long 0
and put it in here as opposed to a default integer 0.
There's not a lot of compelling reasons why someone getting started in C++ would care what size of 0 they put
into a number, but when you read in someone else's code, it can just stop you in your tracks and you say, what the
heck is 0L, so I want you to see it, so that you recognize it when you bump into it.