This module has introduced you to the idea of types that variables have a specific type like integer or bool and
that you have to declare a variable before you use it.
You can declare and use it all in one or you can declare it and then give it a value however many lines later you want
and obviously once it's got a value, you can use it in other calculations, you saw as simply assigning the value
of say i1 into that double. Different types for different kinds of data, they have different lengths, they have
different maximum values in the case of numbers that they can hold.
The compiler knows all this, and will help you as much as it can.
There is also documentation on MSDN if you really start to get worked up about whether or not you can hold billion
in your integer of what have you. You should at least have a faint inkling in the back of your mind that overflow
can happen, that you don't get error messages at runtime when overflow does happen.
The best way to avoid this is don't put numbers into the char type, put numbers into something like int and then
you're almost certainly not going to have a problem with overflow.
Occasionally, I'll see people who have database keys or other really, really big numbers and their putting them
into say a short, something that can hold 32767 and when they crank over to 32768, 9, 70, the run into an overflow
and are really confused and don't know what has happened.
if remember that overflow exists you'll recognize this problem when you come across it.
Just using ints most of the time unless you happen to be in an environment where every single byte counts is the
simplest way to prevent overflow from being a problem for you.
When you want to convert between two types and you're getting a compiler warning about it, stop because remember
the compiler is your friend, and think about whether you actually want to throw away data or truncate a value
whatever it's warning you you're going to do, and if you do then say so by casting.
For now, with the round brackets as we showed in the demo.
Later, after we've covered templates, I'll show you a better and safer way to cast, but for now, casting tells
the compiler, don't warn me about that and that ensures that you'll continue to see warnings that you need to see
from situations that you haven't thought through and weren't doing on purpose and that's when the compiler will
help you out.