I thought I'd start by showing you a very simple template. It's right here.
This is a free function and you can declare and define a function all at once as long as the whole thing is
before you use it. I could have made a header called utility.h in which I declared this function and a cpp
file in which I implemented it, but especially for templates we tend to do it all at once in the include and
rather than have a separate file, which the include statement would have just plunked right here, I decided
to simply put the contents here. You can see the structure of it.
If it wasn't for this first line it would just look like declaring and defining a function.
We have a function called max that returns something called T and it takes T references.
If you're thinking wait, we covered all the types, int, float, da da da; what is T?
T is a placeholder and it's traditional to use the letter T for this placeholder, but you're by no means
obliged to. You could use whatever you like. This line here says,
I'm defining a template and in my template there will be a placeholder for a class,
and despite the word class you can also put fundamental types like ints and things in here,
which I'm going to now refer to for the rest of the time as T.
This says, whatever this is a template of, if it's a template of ints, I mean int.
If it's a template of person objects, I mean person. That's what this function returns.
Its name is max. It takes a T reference, which I'm going to call t1 and another T reference, which I'm going
to call t2. We're using the immediate if and if t1 is less than t2 we'll return t2, otherwise, we'll return
t1. So in other words, if it's a tie we'll return t1. If it's not a tie we'll return whoever's bigger,
using the less than operator. It's hard to imagine a simpler function to write once you've really grasped
_____ if you're done with the difficulty level of this function, but it's really pretty powerful.
In fact, I should point out there's a better implementation of max in the Standard Library and we're only
showing you max so that you have something to look at and to understand.
I'm going to use it. Change my boundaries a little so you can see this whole line.
I'm going to print out max of 33 and 44 is and then I'm going to call the function passing in 33 and 44, and
the compiler's pretty smart. It says, hey, those are integers, you must want the version of max that works
with integers and it'll use that one and return an integer that I can send to cout.
Then I setup a couple of strings and I want to print out the max of them, and again, I just say max of s1, s2
and the compiler says well if you want to pass in a pair of strings you must mean the one that takes strings
and returns a string. And I can even work with Person objects. Here I'm going to print out p1.GetName and
p2.GetName just so I have something to put on the screen, but I'm actually determining the max of p1 and p2,
and that returns a person. So on a person I can use the dot operator and call one of its member functions
and that's how I can get somebody's name. I'm going to run this application and let you see the output.
You can see that the max of 33 and 44 is 44. That fits what we know about numbers, that the max of hello and
world is world. If you think about sorting, W coming after H in the alphabet, okay, that makes sense, and
the max of Kate Gregory and someone else is someone else. Now in order to test if that's right or not you
have to remember how we defined operator less than for Person.
Come back and take a look in Person (Typing). Here's operator&lt;. We compare their arbitrarynumbers.
If one person is less than another, if their arbitrarynumber is less than the other, and the two arbitrary
people I made here, Kate Gregory and someone else, someone else had a number of 456, so that's why they were
the bigger. This is just kind of intuitive and easy to understand.
You're just calling max -- max of two strings, max of two numbers, max of two person objects.
There is a potential problem. I've got to include here BankAccount.h and I'll just open that up and show you
this is a half-written BankAccount class. We're not going to design or write it.
What you need to know about the BankAccount class in its current unfinished state, it doesn't have an
operator&lt;. Person has an operator&lt;, which we discussed in operator overloading and you've just seen the code
for. BankAccount does not.
If I try to do this same behavior with BankAccounts as I've been doing with integers, strings, and persons
I don't get the kind of delightful error messages that I would like to get.
I have to tell you, when you're working with templates sometimes the error messages can be a little opaque.
Here is some code that creates two bank accounts and tries to call the max of b1 and b2.
Let's see what happens when I compile this. I'm just using the keystrokes to build it (Typing).
If failed and the error is, no operator found which takes a left-hand type operand of type 'BankAccount.'
That's not bad. It's even telling me that the problem is here with the less than, but you'd be tempted to go
and say well I'm not calling less than. I don't understand what the problem is.
You kind of need to know that max uses less than and that by calling max you're trying to use less than and
you don't have one. You don't really get a good error message saying you don't implement the right stuff to
use this template. The burden is all on you as the person who wants to use the template, in this case, a
BankAccount developer who wants to use max needs to know what that imposes on BankAccount.
By reading the documentation, if all else fails, maybe by reading the code and looking at it and saying, oh,
I see it uses operator&lt; or it uses operator+ or it uses a member function called compare or whatever it uses,
and if for some reason you have neither documentation nor code, by getting error messages from the compiler.
BankAccount's not eligible to work with max. It just is missing the operators that it needs to work with max
and that's okay. You have to find another way to compare BankAccounts or you can write the operator that's
missing for BankAccounts, but understanding that nobody's going to check for you explicitly.
You'll get errors and eventually you'll figure out what causes the errors, but nobody's going to explicitly
check whether a particular type is okay for use with a particular template or not.
That's your job as the developer.