Here's a template class. This is a very naive accumulator. It keeps a running total.
It's not necessarily a paradigm of exactly how to write accumulators that keep running totals.
There are things that will do this for you in the Standard Library,
but I wanted to choose a class that you could easily see how it worked.
This isn't a header file and there is not Accum.cpp.
That's pretty normal that everything is in the header file, so that it can easily be brought in by the
compiler everywhere that it's used. As with the functions, you notice we start template class T
and then we are defining a class and this is the end of it as usual.
Inside we use T for the type placeholder, just as in the function.
Accum here, if you're making an Accum of ints it'll have an integer total.
If you're making an Accum of floats it'll have a float total.
It has a constructor that takes a starting value. It's probably going to be 0, but we're going to have a
constructor that lets you pass in what your starting value will be and all it will do is,
using C++ initialization syntax, initialize total to that starting value.
Then, we have an operator +=. It returns a type and takes a type reference.
I'll explain the const later. In the material on pointers we'll get into const.
For now, when you take certain things by reference you have to say const,
otherwise, you can't pass in a literal like three, which is a constant.
Treat that as a little bit of a magic word for now. We'll come back to it.
Operator+=, this is just ordinary common or garden operator overloading when you add t onto the total we
should increment total, so total is equal to total + t, and we'll return that value.
That may be of some value if people are chaining them or using them to pass down to other functions
and that kind of thing. Then, I have a member function called GetTotal that provides access to the total
and it is returning type t again, so if totals an int this returns an int,
if totals a float this returns a float, and so on. And I have some code here
that uses it. Now when you instantiate a template class you do explicitly specify the type,
so here I'm saying I have an Accum of int and I've happened to give it a name integers, but you could of
course call it hello or Tuesday or whatever works for you, and I'm passing in the starting value, which makes
sense that we start at 0. And then I just use += a couple times and add more integers onto my accumulator,
and then I ask for the total and print that out. Do the same thing with strings.
I call it strings and this time I initialize it to "" rather than 0 -- that obviously makes more sense for
strings -- and I'm going to put in hello and world. And the rest of the code in this main is commented out,
so let's just run this and show what you get.
So when we put 3 and 7 into the accumulation of integers, we ended up with 10.
And when we put hello and space world into the accumulation of strings, we ended up with a hello world,
so this works as advertised. That's nice. Good, simple, easy to use, and apart from the angle bracket
syntax when you declared them, after that it's just perfectly ordinary class and you just use these
intuitive operators and member functions. Now what do I have commented out down here?
I have attempted to break the rules. I have mentioned a couple times that templates give you type safety.
Integers is an accumulation of integers and its += operator takes an integer reference.
When I try to use a string you can see I'm going to get red wigglies, says no operator += matches these
operands. And similarly, strings is an accumulation of strings and when I try to add in an integer it says,
no operator += matches these operands. I will build it to show you the compiler errors that you get in the
output window. There's a lot more of them and they can be a little more intimidating.
They do contain the same fundamental complaint that you saw in the tip, no operator found which takes a
right hand operator of type ‘const char
And just that, seeing T here and here, is your biggest clue that if it's an accumulation of integers you
should add integers into it and if it's accumulation of strings you should add strings into it.
This kind of type safety is a feature. This is what we want our templates to do for us, to let us write the
code once and use it with a variety of types without forgetting what the types are, keeping all their true
nature as an integer or a string or a person or a bank account, and getting the compiler, our friend the
compiler, to tell us when we mess up. These lines don't compile because our accumulator is type safe and
that's what we want.