Here's the code you just saw in the demo. You start by writing the class out just using a placeholder
instead of the type. We accumulate T, whatever T is, of an ordinary class definition with a private and a
public section, member variables, operators, constructor, member functions, really nothing unusual, and when
you use it you tell the compiler what type you'd like the template instantiated for, so I'd like to
accumulate ints or I'd like to accumulate strings. The compiler will not check on this line and say, is it
okay that you're using this type? Is int appropriate for the Accum class?
It will check as you use or exercise members of Accum, so here you're going to exercise the constructor, and
if there wasn't a constructor that was happy with having the number 0 passed to it for an Accum of ints, if
there wasn't a constructor that's happy with having an empty string passed to it for an Accum of strings,
you'd get a compiler error. If the appropriate constructor was there, but something else wasn't, that's when
you'd find out that there were issues, so just as with the template functions, it can be a little challenging
to understand your compiler errors, but in many cases the compiler errors are actually a feature.
Once you've made an accumulation of ints you can't add strings to it and vice versa, and this type safety is
a big part of what's good about templates.