There's another thing that sets C++ templates apart from the way just about every other language does
generics and that's specialization. The compiler will generate the code using the template for any type you
pass it, but you can say, here's the code I want you to generate for this particular type.
In other words, write the template once generically, here's how to find the max of any two things, and then
again, specifically, here's how to find the max of two employees or two bank accounts.
Why would you need to do that? Well, the thing is that sometimes templates don't work for certain classes.
You saw that max relied on operator&lt; and Accum relies on operator+.
If you haven't overloaded the operator for those classes how could you use the template with those classes --
or if someone has overloaded the operator, but it doesn't do what you want the template to have that operator
mean. When we are working with the simple classes that you see here it's really simple to decide what plus
means. Want to add two people? I guess the only thing that makes sense would be to add their arbitrary
numbers, but what does it mean to add two bank accounts or to compare two employees?
The best thing to do is to add the missing operator. As you know, you can write any operator overload as a
free function, so even if you're not the developer of BankAccount or Employee or Person you could add the
missing operator as a free function. That's an excellent choice and may have other benefits in other parts
of the application as well. It doesn't work if someone's already written it and there are other times when
it's not an option either, so you do have a second choice, which is to specialize the template.
This means you write a version of the template that doesn't have the placeholder in it and that says, here's
how to specifically do the work I want to do for this incompatible class, for this Employee or BankAccount or
Person object. Once upon a time the number one motivation for template specialization was C-style strings,
strings very different from the ones we are using in this material, that were just awkward and horrible and
always needed a special template done for them. It's a little harder to come up with a good reason for
template specialization when our sample templates are so simple, but I want you to see the technique, so I'm
going to show you how to do it. You will need to do it at some point because templates are just such a huge
time-saver and proactivity boost for developers that when you find one that isn't quite right you need to
know how to make it fit your situation.