Let's try to accumulate people.
There's no operator+ defined for people, so it's not going to work, but that's good.
That gives us an opportunity to write a specialization. (Typing)
Here's our accumulator class, as we saw at the end of the last demo, and you may have already noticed that
Person is already in this project. I'm going to paste in some code because watching large quantities of
typing is never entertaining (Typing) and this code works because there is an include of Person.h here also.
You can see that I'm going to declare sort of a dummy person. The first name and last name are both quotes
and the arbitrarynumber is 0. This can be our start. Now, whether we define adding people to mean tacking
all their names together, so that Kate Gregory plus Someone Else is Kate Someone Gregory Else.
Maybe these are our employees and arbitrarynumber is their salary and I want to figure out our total salary burden,
so I'm going to add up everybody's arbitrarynumber. That's probably a better way of thinking about it.
Either way, I've got this sort of dummy person and then I'm going to make an accumulation of persons, called
people, and I'll use that dummy person as the start because the starting value needs to be of the type of
whatever it is we're accumulating. Declare a couple people and stick them in, just exactly in the way that
we declared accumulator and plus equaled them into the accumulator of strings, we'll += our Person objects
into the accumulator of persons. And then people.GetTotal will give us a Person.
We can use the dot syntax and call whatever member variable we want on it, like GetNumber.
It makes sense, but when you go to build it, and I'm just using the key strokes here, (Typing)
whew, error messages like you wouldn't believe. Now, there are an awful lot of them,
but what they basically boil down to is the +. Scroll out this way.
I couldn't figure out what to do in order to handle the += when I wanted to accumulate these Person objects.
Interestingly, it's only going to complain on these two lines.
If I comment out these lines and then build,
the build succeeds.
The compiler has no objection to me declaring an accumulator of Person objects.
It has no objection to me trying to call the GetTotal member function of that accumulator
and it knows that GetTotal will return a Person, so I can call GetNumber on that.
All of this is great. The only part it didn't like was the +=.
And the reason it didn't like the +=? Because Person, for all the operators and goodness that it has,
does not have an operator+, does not have a way to add two Person objects together.
Now I have three opportunities as a developer to try to solve this problem.
One is I could say, ah you know what, I don't need an accumulation of Person objects to figure out
their salary burden. I'll just make an accumulator of int and then I'll go through my people and instead of
adding a person, p1, into my accumulator, I'll call p1.GetNumber and I'll put the resulting integer into my
accumulator. It's okay. It might be repetitive, you might have to type .GetNumber a lot, and you're sort of
pulling some of the business logic about a person out into this calling code, so you have to know to call
GetNumber. You're also of course, giving up type safety. People can put any old integer into that
accumulator and the compiler will let them whereas, when we have an accumulator of Persons we have that type
safety that people can't put anything else in there. Imagine even a very generic loop, if it has to write
different code for Persons by calling GetNumber, that's kind of awkward, so a generically-written loop would
be tripped up by the fact that, oh, but for Persons we can't use the accumulator;
we have to remember to call GetNumber, so let's rule out that possibility.
The next choice is that I could write + for Person.
I have Person.h right here in my project. I could totally go in and write the + operator for Person.
I could write a free function for Person that constructs a new Person that's somehow bigger, based on the
arbitrary number of the person I'm adding it to. It'd be a little bit of a challenge.
There is no public set name function in Person, so I don't know how I'd set the name of the new person.
I could use GetNumber and SetNumber; that's all fine, kind of awkward.
What I want to show you and what is, in many cases, the only approach that will work is to write a template
specialization for Accum that says here's how you handle the special case of Person.
The first time you find a template not working for you, you may find a bit of a work-around, the equivalent
of calling GetNumber and then, oh yeah it works great with ints. That's fine.
You know how to call a member function. I don't need to spend any more time on that.
The second time you find a template that doesn't work for you, maybe you just find a work-around by writing
the operator as a free function or by going into the class and writing the operator.
That's a good choice, especially if having that public operator anyway has other value in your program, but
the day is going to come when you want to use a template, maybe even a template that you wrote.
It doesn't work with your class; there's just no work-arounds;
you can't write the operator because it's already written and you don't want to accept what it does;
and you need to write a template specialization.
It's not a hard thing to do at all, so let me show you. In fact, in the case of accumulator, we gain a real
benefit by writing a specialization, which is that we can actually change the type of our running total while
we're at it. Let's go into Accum.h
and I'm just going to copy all of this (Typing) and put it here.
When you write a specialization the brackets here become empty, but they don't go away.
You still say, I am writing a template. That way the compiler, when it goes to do the template
instantiation, looks at this one too. Here, I say this is the specialization for Person.
This is how you write an Accum of Person objects. Now I have no more T placeholder, so I need to take it
away. Most of the time you run through and just mechanically change T to the type you're writing a
specialization for, which would be person in this case, but you know, it doesn't really make a lot of sense
for the running total of my Person objects to be a person. The name doesn't mean anything, so I'm actually
going to take an opportunity here and say, you know what, my running total is an integer, and I'm going to
an integer for my starting value that I will initialize total to and my += will return an integer.
Now it's going to take a person and it'll return total equals total, but I can't say + t because you can't
add -- take an integer, and add a person to it, so here's where I'll call GetNumber.
And notice the compiler understands that t is a person and gives me IntelliSense here,
so I can call GetNumber and then my GetTotal will return an integer.
All my red wigglies have gone away. I'm going to take this const out of here and
I'm just going to have to ask you to trust me. I told you that it had to be there for when people passed
constants like three. There isn't such a thing really as the equivalent of a literal person and,
at the moment, it wouldn't compile if I left it in.
When we get to the const material you will understand why and that's not very far away, so trust me.
Let's go back to the Main now.
We don't need this fake person for start purposes (Typing) and I can actually just pass in the starting value
that I want of 0, make a couple of people, and now I can accumulate those people.
Now people is of type integer rather than Person, so I --- do need to call GetTotal, but I don't need to call
GetNumber on that, so I can just do this. See we have no wigglies, but I will build it just to confirm.
Build succeeds.
Now let's run it.
10 and hello world are from our old demo; they still work.
And you notice it's also now printed out 579
and if I look at my two people, 123 + 456 is indeed 579, so we successfully accumulated these two people
building up an integer running total and which we were able to print out.
It really wasn't hard to write the specialization for person. When the day comes that you need to write a
template specialization, you know how, and if you find yourself arguing about whether or not template
specializations need to exist, you've seen an example of what they can be good for.