Templates are really not that scary and they are one of the things that make C++ such a high performing
language for you write applications in. They check what's going on at compile time.
When you try to put an inappropriate type into a collection or add it to a running total the compiler
complains, not at runtime, so you can't execute the code that has the problem that's violating type safety.
And at runtime there's no need to check; it wouldn't have compiled if it wasn't a type safe behavior.
That's why your application can be so fast when you use templates, but the productivity is really pretty
dramatic. As long as your types are compatible with the templates you're using it can really package up,
well, just about everything you'll learn as an undergraduate, but in some cases you barely even notice that
you're using the template. If you happen to have a type that doesn't work with a template as written because
you're missing an operator, because you're missing a member function, because your template is special in
some way, then you can provide an operator, if that's appropriate, or write a template specialization and
handle the special cases of your code that the person who wrote the template didn't know was coming.
Now, despite the fact I wrote templates in my demos, you know you are not going to start by writing
templates. You're going to start by using them. I let you see them being written so that you understand
they're very simple and they're not that magical. The power is really in the language feature, not in the
fact that someone went and wrote a 1,000-line template. That said, the templates in the Standard Library are
more complicated than the super simple ones that I showed you. They work with special edge cases.
They check for errors. They understand that sometimes additions might overflow or other unusual
circumstances might arise. Using a template saves you a ton of development time.
Whether it's for collections, whether it's for algorithms, whether it's for simple mathematical
transformations, you shouldn't be writing that code. You're hardly the first person who ever came across the
idea of, wow, we could have a hash table. Obviously, any code you don't have to write, but that you can
count on working is a big benefit, so with templates you get that library power without taking a performance
hit. They are probably the best thing about C++ when you compare it to other languages and now you know how
they work.