In all of the code you've seen so far, you've had some lines that start with this #, or hash, or pound symbol.
Most famously you've seen the include statement. This is a directive to the pre-processor.
It actually just combines the file in together. So when you say include Person.h, it picks a copy of all the
lines in Person.h and plunks them in right where that line appeared.
People can do some very powerful and interesting things with pre-processor directives.
We've talked a couple times about I'm doing a debug, you could also do a release build and things are different
in a debug build then they are in a release build and you can actually use the pre-processor to make different
versions of functions for example, that have more output in them during a debug, and less output in for example
a release build. I don't want to go down the road of all the things you can do with the pre-processor, many
people try to use it as little as possible. They really just use it for includes, but there's one thing you
do need to be able to see when you see it in other peoples code and to be able to do it in your own and that's
the convenience of not having to memorize the structure of all of the headers that your system uses.
There's a concept known as include guards. This is easiest to see in a demo, so let's just get straight into it.