In the demos that I've shown you
so far, I had to comment out this line, Person.h and I'll show you why by taking away the commenting out and building.
See all these errors? Person, class type redefinition, see declaration of Person, What?
What happens is I explain to the compiler what a Person is by including Person.h and then I include Tweeter.h
and if I just go there
you'll see that that first things that Tweeter.h does is include Person.h and the pre-processor Pastes that same
include file in again and then says, what, Person again, well that's an error, our persons already been defined,
we can't have two classes called Person in the same namespace and you get an error.
So because we're really
focusing in that demo on the mechanics of inheritance, I didn't want to get into that, we just commented the line
out, but obviously we have to fix something about that.
Now the old fashion way would be to have someone include both files, get an error, and then say I get it, Tweeter
brings in Person, so I don't need to bring in Person, so I'll just take this line away.
I don't like that. I don't like having to build a tree in your head of all the possible things that have been
included by other things. You just should be able to say what you use and then let them work it out amongst
themselves and there are a variety of ways to do it, here is a way that many, many developers use.
You go into the header file and we're going to add directives in here that basically prevent it from ever being
included twice. So if someone tries to include Person.h a second time, the header file itself will recognize
that it's already been included and not define the class again and therefore not trigger the error messages
and we're going to do this using some pre-processor directives that can define arbitrary constants and people use
this to say for example, define pi to be 3.14 15 etc and then they can use pi in their calculations.
We're going to define some constants that really just indicate, we must have been this way before because this
constant is already defined. Once you've defined a constant, you can test to see if it's defined or not and
that's how we'll know what's going on. So the constant by tradition, is based on the name of the file, that
way they won't conflict or clash with each other. So for example, I might define _Person_H and that's a variable
that represents the name of this file Person.h. If that's already defined, we must have already included this file.
If it isn't defined yet, we haven't yet included this file.
So before I define it, I test, ifnotdef _Person_H and then I'm going to put the end of that all the way down here.
So what's happening is, if Person.h is not yet defined, great, in comes the whole rest of the file.
We define Person.h, we declare the Person class and everything is as before, but if Person.h is being included for
a second time, when the pre-processor is doing that including and it reaches this ifnotdef, it says, oh but it
is defined, okay, we'll skip down here to the endif and as a result Person does not get included again.
So let's Build this
and you can see there's no error messages, this works perfectly. The main file
ClassesAndObjects can now include Person and Tweeter without worrying that they have some kind of relationship or
that one includes the other, or that it matters what order, it all just kind of works the way that it should
and this pattern is called an include guard. Whatever your arguments for or against include guards are, please don't
compiler performance be one of them. This is a relatively high performing way to solve this particular problem,
but it's not the only way. There is another way that isn't standard.
So this is standard it will work in every C++ compiler in the universe.
They all understand the idea of defining a constant and they understand the idea of testing against the constant
and some of them, for example Visual Studio, can also be reasonably smart about realizing the endif is at the
very end of the line, so I don't even need to process the rest of the file.
There is another approach, that you can take and in fact, when we added that class using the Wizard,
Visual Studio took this approach for us and that's this directive here, pragma.
As you can see it's a pre-processor directive just like include, or define, or ifnotdefined and pragma, once
says, this particular file should only be included once in each compilation unit.
It's the same things behind the scenes, the compiler generates the unique identifier and makes sure that if it
gets included again it doesn't actually process it again.
Some people find this more readable, some people find it less readable.
There may be compilers out there that don't recognize it in which case you would need to write the old include
guard way anyway. You're welcome to use pragma once if you prefer it to include guards.
You should be to recognize include guards when you see them
in someone else's header files and understand what's going on and if you're copying someone else's code for your
own purposes and you copy include guards, make sure you change the name of the defined variable that you're using
to guard the include with to something that represents your new file name otherwise you're get really strange
behavior where I know I'm including this file, but the compiler's acting like I'm not because if two files actually
both test the same variable, they can't both get included, that's never going to be a good thing.
So you have to understand how include guards work in order to be able to understand other people's code.
If you would prefer to do
the prama once and you're only going to be working in Visual Studio, or Visual C++ Express, that's fine, pragma once
will work beautifully, they're both available to you.