This module has covered a lot of ground. You've seen how you can make your own classes and then just declare
instances of those classes on the stack, just like fundamental types.
So you can make an integer, you can make a person, you can make something that is of type enum, just on the stack.
When you make an object, and instance of a class on the stack like this, it's lifetime is managed for you.
When the instance goes out of scope, the object gets cleaned up.
Any memory it was using is released and the destructor runs, which might close a file, close a database connection,
or in the demos you saw in the module, just write a message on the screen.
You also saw the order in which constructors and destructors run when you're using inheritance hierarchy
for your classes. You know both user defined types, Person, Tweeter, or string, which while it wasn't defined by
me as a user, it was defined by a user and not by the language itself, and the fundamental types like int, and
double, and bool, they're all just as real as each other and they can be used in the same ways.
They can initialized, they can go in and out of scope, they have their lifetimes managed, there's no special
distinction that says, when it's a user defined type you have to create it this way.
You create them the same way and they live the same kind of lives.
Your classes can do whatever fundamental types can do and one of the most important classes to any developer is a
string class. There's one in the standard library, which you can get started using from day one.
It's a great example of how important user defined types can be in every application.
Just because their defined by a user doesn't mean their defined by you, it just means they're not built into
the language itself. Now that you understand objects, and variables, and types, you understand I hope why the
complier is your friend and you're ready to write applications that actually do at besides just declaring variables
and putting values in them.