An object is an instance of a class. You might define the class of it might be defined in a library like the string
class that we've been using from the standard library. You define your own classes with the class keyword and
if you know how to do it in some other languages like java or C#, you may believe you know how to do it in C++.
You'll mostly right, the first thing that trips up a lot of people with experience in other languages is there's
a trialing semicolon, so it's class, then the name of the class open brace bracket, all of the definition of the class,
closed brace bracket and then a semicolon after that last closed bracket.
A lot of people forget that one and I mention it because it can cause some really weird error messages that happen
on the line after where you define the class. As well, the inside of the class you don't go line by line this
element is public, this element is private, this element is private, private, private.
Instead you have a section, you say from here down its public and then you hit the private keyword and from
here down its private and if you don't say anything, the default is that it's private.
C++ won't stop you from declaring public member variables, but you shouldn't, you should have private member
variables and a mix of public and private functions depending on your design, you're architecture, what they're
used for. So functions that you're offering to other classes to use will be public and those that are your own
convenience functions will generally be private. I've mentioned before that one of the hallmarks of C++ is that
your classes and classes from libraries you're using really have the same rights and responsibilities and
abilities as the fundamental types. So you declare instances of employees or insurance policy or whatever your
business objects are just the same way that you declare instances of integers or any of the other fundamental
types that we went through in the fundamental types module.
When you want to use that object, chances are what you want to do is call some member function of the object or
possibly if you made a public variable access a member variable of the object and you would do that using a . syntax.
You've seen the scope resolution operator before, the :: between the namespace std and the classname string
for example. It also is used for static member variable and static member functions classname:: and then the
element that you want to access. We're going to start simpler than that though because before you can start to
access member variables and functions of objects we need to be clear about how to define a class and that's
where we need to start.