So let's write a class and then use it. Come over to
Visual C++ Express and I'll use this New Project link
on the Start page to New Console application as usual,
and I'll put the project in my projects directory here
and call it ClassesAndObjects.
We go through the Wizard as always and just check here, Console application, Precompiled headers, nothing else
is set hit finish.
You can see that the new project template generates a main, which we'll come back to, but what I want to start
with is our class. In theory, I could simply start to type the definition of the class right here in this file.
It's possible for your C++ application to be one giant file.
I'm going to create specific files and the project system will pull them together when we build.
So I'll start by right clicking the project and saying Add, a New Item
and I'll add a C++ File. I'm going to call my class Person, so I'd like a file called Person.cpp.
and there's absolutely nothing in the file, it's simply an empty file that I can do whatever I like.
I could type the definition of the class in here. I'm actually going to add this sort of magic invocation line
that you'll see any time a project made with Visual C++ Express or any other version of Visual Studio, uses the
precompiled headers. The very first line of your file needs to be this include of the standard heads, stdafx.h.
If it's even second, you get error messages, so I like to put that in right away so that don't forget.
Now the next thing I could do is to actually type the definition of my class.
So I'm going to make a class called Person open brace, here's where the definition of the class belongs, then I'll
have a closed brace and then I'll have that trailing semicolon that I mentioned and in here, all the definition
of Person. However, I obviously intend to use this Person class more than just here in Person.cpp.
I intend probably to use it over here
and create some instances and so on from inside this main.
In order to do that, main would have to know that Person was a class and that's where the header file comes in.
So I'm going to Add another File into my project
a Header File, which I will call Person.h
and I'm going to take this definition of the Person class, Cut it out of here,
and Paste it into here. Now, I can define Person in the Person.h header file and include that header file
both here in Person.cpp and here
in ClassesAndObjects.cpp so that I can use Person objects.
Now what am I going to put in my definition of a Person? Well, we all have names, a firstname lastname, so those
seem like good candidates and they are probably best represented as strings, so I'm going to add an include statement
to let me use string from the standard library. So then here, inside my definition of my class, I'm going to put
these three member variables. By default, everything is private unless I say that it's in the public section,
but just as a matter of politeness for people who read your code, it's a good idea to specify things.
So I'm going to say, private and you notice it turns blue, keyword and the : is important and now everything that
list after this is going to be private until we bump into the word public.
So I'm going to make a string for the Person's firstname and another string for the Person's lastname and then
just so that we have something in this class that's not a string I'm going to add an integer and I'm going to
call it arbitrarynumber. Depending on your business problem that you're solving this might be somebody's salary,
it might be somebody's age, it might be somebody's number of dependents, it could be anything.
It's just a number just so we don't all have strings inside Person here.
So this header file Person.h is now doing a pretty good job of declaring the Person class.
Let's go into Person.cpp
and we'll add this include Person.h and I love this IntelliSense to help me remember the names of headers, Person.h
is exactly what I want and then we'll come here
into the main and include Person.h in here also. Once we've done that, this piece of code now knows what a
Person is so I can write lines like this Person p1, Person p2, the same as declaring an integer or anything else
the type and the then name that you want to call it and presto, I have some objects.
Now these two objects, p1 and p2 are both of type Person, but just as if I had two integers i and j, their values
are entirely independent and so it is with these people.
This code allocates a Person's worth of memory for p1 and a Person's worth of memory for p2, and it's there ready
to have values in it, and ready to be used. The values for most types in C++ are not defaulted or initialized
for you. It's possible for objects to have them defaulted and initialized, it's not possible for integers.
So if I just say integers i, it doesn't have a value it just has sort of random stuff that happened to be in memory.
When we created a string in earlier demos, it was initialized to "" to an empty string.
That's done because it's a class. The person who wrote the class decided if you just say that you have a string
it should be an empty string and we have the ability, which you'll see shortly to do that for person, but I haven't
yet done that for person. So Person p1 will have memory for a string for firstname, memory for a string for lastname
and because their strings they'll be initialized to "" and it'll have memory for the integer for arbitrarynumber
and that won't be initialized, so it'll just be whatever number happens to be in that piece of memory and the
same will be true for p2. I'm going to show you in the debugger how this looks so that you can see what's happening
with those variables. So I'll set a breakpoint on the initialization of the first Person and Run.
We'll have to Build it first, I had unsaved changes when I hit Run, that's fine, Saves my changes it's going to
build for me
and when we reach this breakpoint, before we've executed this line, p1 is full of things that are showing debugger
here in the watch window as being bad pointer, don't worry about that.
Once we go over that line, you'll see that firstname has been initialized to "", lastname to "" and
arbitrarynumber is just some random stuff that happened to be in that memory location, p2 is still uninitialized.
We step over this line, is firstname and lastname have also been initialized to "" and the arbitrarynumber again,
it looks like the exact same number, that's because this is a debug build and in order to help developers spot
uninitialized variables being used, in debug builds the memory is sort of prepopulated with signal values.
However, p1 and p2 are completely independent each with their own copies of these three variables and I'll show
you that very shortly. Let's stop the debugger because obviously in order to demonstrate that these are independent
we need to be able to get values into the variables. To put something in p1's firstname, put something in p2's
firstname and see that they are different and that changing one didn't change the other.
There are a couple of ways to do this, but since we were talking about initializing, this is the time to talk
about the constructor. The constructor for a class has the same name as a class and it's used to initialize
instances of that class or objects. So I'm going to add a constructor to Person. I'll go into the header file
where we've declared the class and I'll add a public section because obviously this constructor isn't much good
if people can't call it and the name has to be Person and it doesn't have a type before it the way some other
things might because constructors, they just don't. I have to specify what kinds of values can be passed into
constructor to initialize a Person. We could choose no values at all.
When we make a Person their person is "" their lastname is "" and their arbitrarynumber is 0 or -1, 107, or
whatever you'd like it to be. But a more useful constructor take values and puts them into the member variables.
So that's what I'm going to code here. I'm going to say, that I take a string from the standard library called
first and a string from the standard library called last and an integer called arbitrary and that's what this
function is defined to be and I put a semicolon here. In the header file, I'm only saying that this function exists.
Remember that other files include this header. They only need to know that the function exists, they don't need
to know the code for it. So we'll go over here
to put the code for it. To code the constructor, to code anything inside the cpp file, I have to give the full
name, which includes the class name. When we're here in Person.h
and I'm typing in what person takes, you can see I'm inside class Person, I'm between the open brace and the
closed brace of person.
Here I'm not, I'm just kicking around in space and so when I want to code that person function, I have to say
before that, Person:: this is the class name and this is the function name.
The function name for a constructor is always the same as the class name.
It's possible, although it would be horrible practice, to have in this file the implementations of a bunch of
different constructors from a bunch of completely unrelated classes and the complier could work it out.
It wouldn't be a good thing to do because humans who are going to read your code couldn't work it out, but the
compiler doesn't demand one file is for one class and as a result you have to specify, here's what I'm doing.
I'm implementing the constructor for Person. Now I have read wiggles right now because the constructor for Person
takes those three parameters the firstname, the lastname, and the arbitrarynumber and I haven't typed that part yet.
So I'm actually just going to Copy that part
and I'm using Ctrl+Tab to flip between the files. I'm just going to put this up onto a single line to make the rest of it a
little more readable, and to define the body of the function I need an open brace and a closed brace and in between
is the body of the constructor. Now here's how a lot of people would like to write this constructor.
They say sure you've got a member variable called firstname, I remember that, so we'll use that put first into that
and another member variable called lastname, we'll put last into that, and you got a member variable called
arbitrarynumber, and we'll put arbitrary into that. This isn't exactly wrong.
I can build this
and although I get an error, it's not an error in Person.ccp, you can see here Person.cpp generates code, complies
and then it moves onto the next file. I will discuss this error later, but here this code is fine from the
compliers point of view. It is however not the correct to write and this is something that people who are comfortable
in other languages come over to C++, they write code like this all the time and then experienced C++ people tell
them that their wrong and they say, how can I possibly be wrong?
It complies, it runs, it puts values in my variables, I don't know what you're talking about and it has to do with
this idea of how you default or initialize the member variables of the object.
When you code it this way, what ends up happening behind the scenes, when you create p1, is that first, all of
member variables are given their memory and if they have default values they're defaulted, and then when we hit
this open brace bracket, all of the member variables exist, they have memory and they've even been initialized
if they can be initialized, and then their values are changed.
If setting the value into a string were terribly expensive, which it isn't, this would be a real waste of time.
First setting it up to its default value, then changing to the value you really wanted.
Obviously for something like an integer where there is no default value, this is harmless and for strings, frankly
it's not a very big deal, but it's a bad habit to get into.
There are also some times when it's actually not possible to write this code, especially later when you get into
inheritance you'll see that. So you want to do things right from beginning and in C++ right means using something
called initializer syntax. When your initializers are expensive, initializer syntax is one of the ways you make
your application perform better. One of the ways that C++ gets really obsessive about performance is saying
don't waste your time initializing to a default value and the immediately changing the value, just initialize it
in the first place using the value you intend to use and that's done with initializer syntax to pass along the
parameters that came in, in the constructor. C++ certainly likes to be terse sometimes and the syntax for
initializers is a single character we just type this : and then we rattle them off with a member variable name
and what we want to initialize it to. So we say I want to initialize firstname to first, and then, I'm going to
initialize lastname to last, and I can have line breaks if I want them, it just helps to make things readable, and
I want to initialize arbitrarynumber to arbitrary. Once I've done that, I don't need the body anymore and this
is a very common pattern to see in a constructor that the open brace and the closed brace have really nothing
in between them. So the role that the constructor is serving here is to be a traffic cop and direct those three
parameters off to these initializers of my three member variables.
The benefit here is that if it costs to initialize that firstname, we're only going to initialize it once using
the parameter that was passed in rather than once to a default value, and then assigning it the value that was
passed in. So if I Build this again, you can see that Person compiled without an error.
There's no output related to Person, but again we're getting these errors in ClassesAndObjects and now I want to
show you what those are. So we'll go over and look here, it says Person : no appropriate default constructor available.
So a constructor is this function with the same name as the name of the class and a default constructor is a
constructor that doesn't take any argument and you know this is a fair complaint.
If we look at all of the constructors for Person, there's only one and it takes three arguments.
There isn't one that doesn't take any arguments, but some of those may be saying, I don't understand
because before this way okay. Before when we said p1 we didn't pass in any arguments and the compiler had no
complaint then. When you don't write any constructors you get a default constructor for free.
It doesn't do anything, but it exists and it keeps the compiler happy.
You can't see it, it's not generated for you by some sort of Wizard it's actually written by the compiler every
time you compile your program. The minute you have one constructor, the compiler is in effect saying, I see you
know what you're doing. Right, fine, if you wanted a default constructor I guess you would have written a
default constructor and so it doesn't make one for you anymore and that makes this code
say, well what I need here is a constructor that doesn't take any arguments since I don't have any arguments and
then it can't find one, and then you get this error. You can see if I hover here, no default constructor exists
for class Person. I could write a default constructor for class Person that would be trivial, but the only reason
we wrote this constructor that takes the three arguments was so we could call it.
So I need to change this code to call that constructor. So the syntax for initializing objects using a constructor
that takes arguments is with round brackets. You may remember from the other demo you can say, int i and then on
a later line you can say i=2, or you can say int i=2, or you can say int i(2) that also initializes.
That round bracket syntax is the way that you'd pass one more parameters to constructors of objects.
So I can say here, " I'm going to make a person based on me, so is pass in Kate", and my arbitrarynumber can be
123 and then we'll come down to this next line and we'll do someone else and their number can neighbor 456.
So now I'm constructing my two different Person objects p1 and p2 and I'm using that three argument constructor
to get values into them. So let's run again.
So if we step over this first line, you can see that p1 has those values, drag this over a little so you can see
all parts of it and if I Step Over here, you can see that p2 has completely different values and that changing p2
didn't change anything in p1. Hopefully, that's not a very big surprise.
So we'll Stop debugging and now I'm going to briefly have a bad practice so that I can show you something and then
I'll make it right again. I'm going to make one of my member variables public.
You really shouldn't do this, but it lets me easily write some code to set its value without having to get into
the ways you really should be setting values. We'll do that shortly.
So I'm making arbitrarynumber public and then I can come in here
and say, with the . syntax, p1.arbitrarynumber = 124 and we'll do for p2 also change the arbitrarynumber to 457
and we can run this,
and just as we step through, you can see p1 being created with value 123 for arbitrarynumber and now you see it
changed to 124, p2 being created and arbitrarynumber changing to 457.
This . syntax, the objects name . field or member variable, or member function, or whatever part of it you want
to talk to, happens whenever you're dealing with instances that have their own independent values.
So p1 and p2 have their own arbitrarynumbers, they are accessed with a . syntax.
Public member variables are a bad plan.
There's more appropriate, kind of best practices, ways to deal with
setting values in member variables. So I want to take this code back out, but just to demonstrate the simplicity
of the . syntax, the IntelliSense to help you access that member of the class and then the pretty consistent pattern
for talking to pieces of an object.