You saw in the demo how objects can be created. What you saw without realizing that you saw it also, was objects
going away. Objects have a lifetime and when you declare an object like that, Person p1, we say that's allocated
on the stack. The constructor is called, memory is allocated for the object, the object is initialized and it
just generally comes into being, when the flow of the control reaches the particular line on which the
object is declared. So at the moment that we're on that line, Person p1 and we step over it in the debugger and
having stepped over it, we've allocated the memory, we've used the constructor to initialize the object and the
objects sitting there alive, but p2 is not yet. Then we go over the next line in the debugger and now p2 is allocated
and constructed. When those two objects what we say go out scope, which means reaching a closed brace bracket
in most cases, then the memory is freed and the opposite of a constructor, known as a destructor, runs.
Destructors don't have to be written, they don't have to do anything.
The case of Person, there's no need to write a destructor to clean up at the end of the objects lifetime.
There are some kinds of objects for which you do need to write a destructor and in C++ we have this saying or
this idiom RAII, Resource Acquisition is Initialization and that's a way of thinking that says, if I have a
resources that needs to be managed, let's say an open file or a database connection, or even something like the
Windows cursor. In the constructor I will acquire the resource, that is I'll open the file, I'll open the
database connection, I'll change the Windows Cursor to a weight symbol and I'll do the opposite and release the
acquisition and cleanup in the destructor. So I'll close the file in the destructor.
I'll close the database connection in the destructor. I'll put the cursor back to where it should be in the destructor.
and this pairing up the resources are required in the course something and released in the destructor, means that
developers really don't need to think about it. They create an object on the stack, constructor goes off, stuff
gets acquired. Later it goes out of scope, destructor goes off, stuff gets released and in the old school days,
if you're a person who ever worked in C, where you have to say now remember to close things when you're done with
them, remember to open things before you use them. This approach says, look relax, when you construct the object
we will acquire whatever needs to be acquired in order for you to use the object.
We'll open the file, or we'll open the connection, or whatever and when you're done with it, when it goes out of
scope, it will cleanup itself. You may have heard that in C++ you have all this complicated difficult memory
management and you have to delete things and all this, that's just not true.
There are some ways of programming in C++ that puts a tremendous burden on the developers to just remember a million
things, but the RAII approach which says, when you make an object the constructor gives it to you ready to use
whatever needs to be opened is opened, whatever needs to allocated is allocated and the destructor will close it
up and clean it up for you. That way, when people especially when you get to use objects from a library, they
just work, they do what they need to do. I'm going to stay away from opening files, making connections to databases,
changing Windows cursors because they're reasonable difficult tasks to do, but I am going to show you how this works.