I'm going to come back into
Visual C++ Express and come into the Person class
and I'm going to add a line to the constructor that just prints out a statement that we're in constructor, that'll
help to be able to track when the constructor runs and after we add a destructor, we'll also be able to check
when the destructor runs. I'd like to print something out on the screen, so that means I need to include iostream.
Then I can just come in here and say, in the standard library I'd like to use cout and I'll send it constructing
and just so I can tell them apart, I'll send the firstname and a space and the lastname and then an endline character.
Now every time we construct something, they'll put output written out that we can take a look at.
I'm now going to add a destructor to this class. It doesn't really have any genuine work to do, we don't allocate
or acquire any resources when we're initializing a person, so we don't need to clean any up, but I'm just going
to add one so that we can have an out statement and the rules for a destructor is that the name is this ~ followed
by the name of the class and it doesn't take any parameters
and then in here, I'm going to implement the destructor. When writing the constructor, we have to start with saying
the name of the class and then the name here of the destructor and it doesn't take any arguments and it has an
open and a close. I'm just going to Copy this line
and now we're going to print out when the destructor goes off.
I could just
run this code as is, I'm going to make one small change, I mentioned that scope ends when control reaches a brace
bracket, you can have a brace bracket for whatever reason you want.
You might have them as part of some ifs and loops and things we haven't covered yet, but you can also just
randomly have them and what happens when I do this is as we go through, first p1 will be constructed, then p2 will
be constructed, then when we hit this closed brace, p2 will go out of scope and be cleaned up and the destructor
will go off. Then we'll return from the function and that will cleanup p1, p1 will get destructed.
Let me prove this to you. I don't need to do this under the debugger, I'll just use Ctrl+F5, let it Build.
First we constructed p1, which is me, then p2 which is someone else.
Then because we reached that closed brace, we destructed p2 and finally, destructed p1.
Understanding the scope of objects that you allocate is important to know.
The constructor goes off when control reaches that line. The destructor goes off when the object goes out of scope.
I didn't need to keep track of these Person objects myself and clean them up, destructors went off simply because
control reached this closed brace and that took the object out of scope.
The important thing to understand is that much of this is done for you automatically and it's an important part of
thinking like a C++ developer.