I want you to be able to read and understand C++ code that come across and C++ code that I show you and in order
to do that, I really want to minimize the times when I say, don't worry about this little magic invocation, we'll
cover it later and when I have to do that, I want to come and close that loop up again as soon as I can.
A couple things therefore that I want to talk about now because I think you're going to be able to understand the
code I show you better, if you've seen these things. First I want to mention struct.
Struct is a lot like a class. It's a user defined type.
It's often used for what we call plain old data or POD classes. They don't really have any business logic.
Take a point for example, it has and x and a y, it doesn't have a method to validate it and make sure that it's
legitimate point, or to put it in the database, or to update it for a new fiscal year, it's just an x and a y.
Struct however can have everything that classes cam have.
They can have functions in them, include a constructor and a destructor, but they only have one difference,
literally once difference. I mentioned that if you don't say public versus private in a class the default is private.
In a struct, the default is public, that's the only difference and you should never use the default anyway you
should always say the following stuff is private, the following stuff is public and then that turns into there being
no difference whatsoever between a struct and a class.
As a matter of practice, most developers like to use structs for POD classes and classes for full on classes, but
it could go either way. I've shown you how to write classes. I should show you at least the syntax for inheritance.
Some of the significances and importantance of inheritance will really only come into play as we move into doing
more with our classes, but I'll show you how inheritance works to get you started for that and I wanted to talk
about namespaces. We've been using the std namespace on and saying std:: string to day this is a standard class
from the standard library. A little bit more about namespaces and a little less typing, just so that your code
will be a little more , the way everyone else's cod is and then enum, which is a concept in a lot of languages
just a way to give names to constants. The C++ enum is a little bit different from some other languages enum,
so I want you to see it and know how it works.