I'm going to add a class into this project. It needs to be a special kind of person, something that can inherit
from person but add capability and noun that some people are, but not all people are.
I'm just going to choose to represent someone who is on Twitter, a Tweeter if you will, and a Tweeter will be a
person with some extra capabilities or some extra member variables.
In our case specifically, a twitterhandle. Now I could create this class the same way I created the Person class,
by hand adding a cpp file, and an h file and typing some code into them.
I want to show you another way to add a class into a project and to be honest, it's the way you'll probably use
most often. I wanted you to see it how to do it by hand first and then how Visual Studio helps you.
So I'll come up here to the Project, right click, choose Add, and now scroll down here to class.
I'll choose a C++ Class
and this brings up a Class Wizard to help you add classes into your system.
You give it a Name, let's say Tweeter, and you can see that it's naming the h file and the cpp files that it's
going to generate for you. I want Tweeter to be inheriting from Person, so to have a Base class, that's the C++
terminology of person, and we'll leave this Access as public for now and leave these things unchecked because
that way I don't have to explain them just yet. I'll click Finish
and you can see that it adds the header file Tweeter.h and the cpp file, Tweeter.cpp to my project.
It generates a constructor and a destructor for me
and implementations with nothing in the of those two methods and you can see the appropriate includes have also
been put in my file for me.
I want to have strings, I'm going to make the Person's twitterhandle for example a string, so let's and include
of string (typing) and I'll add a private section (typing) and a member variable for their twitterhandle.
This constructor that has been generated for me, doesn't take any parameters, but if a Tweeter is a person and a
person has a firstname, a lastname, and an arbitrarynumber then a Tweeter has a firstname, a lastname, and a
arbitrarynumber, that's the whole point of inheriting and we'd like to have a constructor that can set them and
as well a Tweeter has a twitterhandle. So I'm going to take
these three parameters from our Person.h
Put them in here along with a fourth parameter for the handle and then these will be the four parameters to the
constructor in the implementation
file and again, I'm going to use the initialization syntax and initialize the parts of Tweeter that are a person,
as well as the part that is special in a Tweeter. You might think the way to do that would be the way we did it
over in Person. So I'd say initialize firstname to first, firstname is part of person.
We have a perfectly good way to get a person object initialized, and that is with its constructor, and that's what
I'm going to use here. So I'll say, I want to use the Person constructor and pass in first, last, and arbitrary
and I will also initialize twitterhandle using handle.
So with this approach, I'm relying on the Person constructor to handle initializing the Person part of Tweeter and
I'm using this syntax to initialize the twitterhandle part of Tweeter.
I will Copy from
this implementation, print statement
to put some stuff on the screen and in order for that to work
I'm going to need this include line
and I'm going to add the word tweeter here and instead of putting out the firstname and the lastname, is just
put out their twitterhandle and then we'll put that down here in the destructor. Let's come back into the
main class and instead of having some Person only, we're going to also have some Tweeters so I'll include Tweeter.h.
Now for reasons I'll explain very shortly, I'm going to comment out the include of Person.
I'm going to leave Person p1 as myself and change this Person to being a Tweeter and we need to pass this fourth
parameter into the constructor, I don't actually know someone else's handle so we'll use whoever and apologizes
if that's someone real Twitter handle. Just to really clarify what's happening with scope, I'm going to add another
line here (typing)
which will work best if it has the header. So we're going to construct a Person.
We're going to construct a Tweeter, when we hit this closed brace, we're going to destruct the Tweeter, then we're
going to print out this line, then we'll destruct the person.
Let's let his run with Ctrl+F5
and you can see what happens. Let's pull this over
a bit and let you compare the code to the output.
First we constructed the Person object, then we constructed the Tweeter object.
As part of constructing the Tweeter object, the Person part of its constructor went off and said constructing
Someone Else and after that was complete the derived class, the Tweeter part of the constructor went off, put the
twitterhandle value basically in. We hit this closed brace and the destruction happened in the opposite order.
First we ran the derived class destructor which said destructing tweeter@whoever and then the compiler ran the
Person part of the destructor which said destructing someone else.
Then we printed out this line that says after innermost block and finally, the destructor went off for p1.
This sort of order of operations that the base part constructor happens first and then the derived part constructor
is really important. It means that code in a derived constructor and count on its based class part being fully
initialized already and it also means that when you're destructing that the derived part cleans up its own stuff
and then relaxes and lets the base class cleanup it's part.
So if the base class managed a file, the derived class would know the file was still open during its destructor
and then base class might close the file for example and this is a really important aspect of understanding scope
and of understanding resources acquisition is initialization.
It's taken care of for you and it's taken care of you in a specific order every time.