It's time to cleanup some lose ends and one of the most annoying lose ends is having to keep typing std:: whatever
before say cout. This is the namespace std and the functionality that comes from the standard library is all in
this namespace, which is wonderful. It means that I can call my classes whatever I like.
If I want to write a string class, I can write a string class and I'll be able to tell them apart by talking about
standard string and Kate's great library:: string and it would possible to mix and match them in the same application
without any confusion and that is fantastic. It means that no words are really reserved.
String is available to be the name of your class, as long as you don't mind confusion in the minds of other developers.
Everything that's part of the standard library is inside the standard namespace and you can have things with exactly
the same name in your namespace, if you want. My problem is with having to type the name of the namespace every
single time I use these classes when I haven't written my own string or my own console out.
Well of course, I don't have to. Of course, there's a mechanism to get around it and it's as simple as calling
it out like this. I can say for example, I will be using from the standard library, cout.
Or I will be using from the standard library, endl and if I do that, then I can come down here and just call them
cout and endl. Now that in itself is a big improvement.
This isn't any kind of directive about going and picking certain things out of the larger library, it doesn't change
the size of my executable for example, it simply a convenience to the compiler and saying, whenever you see just
plain cout, I mean std::cout, I mean the standard cout, I just don't want to type it's whole name every time.
When you're going to use a number of things from the same namespace, it can get tiring to keep adding more things
so there's another approach. I can come into say the Person class
where I'm using both cout and I'm also using string, I could come here and say using the entire namespace std.
Having done that I can now go through and take away in front of every string, as well as in front of cout and endl.
and you can see I don't have any red wiggles, the compiler is fine with that.
Now there are some languages in which using has a different meaning, it has to do with controlling scope, we have
brace brackets for scope, using never has anything to do with scope.
Using is only about these namespace directives, it doesn't link new code in or add new references, anything it's
simply telling the compiler, when I say cout and you think, I don't know what you're talking about, quick go and
see if it's std::cout and if it is, we're both happy.
So it's basically what the compiler does with identifiers it doesn't immediately recognize like string, cout,
and endl in this example. Sometimes people want to put this using namespace whatever in a header file, that is a bad plan.
Right now, I can use Person and still have my own string class.
Person works with standard strings my code could work with my own strings.
The minute there's a using namespace standard inside Person, now everyone who wants to use Person has to agree not
to have collisions with something that is in std and that's too big of thing to ask.
You can do it in a cpp file, don't do it in an h file.
In a header file, you can call everything out by its full name or have individual using statements like the ones
we had here
for individual parts of the standard namespace, but I prefer to see those using namespace whatever's only in cpp
file and not in h files. Now my code looks a little neater, has a little less punctuation in it, and I think it's
easy to understand and read it as long as you can remember cout is from the standard library, string is from the
standard library, but Person and Tweeter are not, they're no longer being decorated as being different.
Now of course Visual Studio will help you, so if I hover over Person, it shows me that it's just class Person, but
if I hover over
say string in here, it's got a big long definition and it's got std:: and in its definition as a reminder that this
is the standard string from the standard library.