So far, we've worked with fundamental types like integers, and
floating point numbers, objects whether defined in the library like string, in the standard libraries, or in our
own code like Person and Tweeter and I've mentioned structs which are essentially identical to classes.
Just to round the picture out, I want to talk about enums. So I'm going to add another header file into this system
and I'm going to call it status.h
and in here I'm going to define an enum called Status and like a class an enum has its definition inside braces
and has a ; at the end of that last brace and we simply list out the possible Statuses.
Now an interesting thing about C++ enums for people who have come from other languages is that when you use them,
you only use these internal things. So I wouldn't say Status.Pending, I would just say Pending.
That means that these names need to be unique. I can't have Approved as part of a Status enum and also have it as
part of a completely different unrelated enum. Very often, when you read other people's code, you will therefore
see decorations, bits of extra words like it might be status.pending, status.approved, status.canceled, to keep
that uniqueness in an enum. I'm going to keep these ones simple and we'll just use one.
So if I go back into my main
I'll just declare a Status s give it a value like pending. You can see the compiler saying what, don't know what
you're talking about? It's because I haven't included the header file.
So let's go up here status.h, give it a minute, it should become content down here and once I've declared the variable,
I can obviously change this value at anytime just as did with integers and so on.
So I can say now that s = Approved and that's a legitimate thing to do.
So if I Run the application, under the debugger,
and we'll just step through all this part, and see here s is just an arbitrary value at the moment --- control hasn't
reached that line, so it hasn't been initialized yet. We step over that line and the debugger actually shows the
enum value Pending and we go down to this line, it shows the enum value Approved.
So in the debugger I can see the word value rather than any underlying number that's inside of it and it saves
you as a developer having to memorize a lot of strange numeric values for error codes and status and the like and
it makes debugging simpler as well.