In this course, I am going to teach you to how to write C++ applications using Visual Studio exclusively.
Visual Studio is what's called an Integrated Development Environment.
It has an editor where you can type your code, a compiler that transforms the code you typed into something
that can be executed, and a debugger that helps you observe it executing and learn where you may have a
problem and fix that problem, and a whole pile of other related tools as well.
Now, there are other ways to compile your applications, you can get standalone compilers, Microsoft has a
number of free ones that it distributes as part of its SDK, and other people
make and either give away or sell C++ compilers.
But Visual Studio is more than just a compiler, and you won't be typing a lot of commands at the command line
and learning some strange syntax in order to pull your projects and applications together if you use Visual Studio.
Specifically, I am going to use Visual Studio Express, which is one of many different additions of Visual Studio.
Now Express is not a single thing, there is Visual C++ Express, Visual C# Express, and so on, as a version for
Visual Basic for web development, for phone development and Express is completely and totally free.
It's free, even if you use it to make applications that you sell for money, that is all fine.
There is a little functionality in some of the other additions of Vision Studio, that is not in Express.
I won't be showing any of that functionality in this material, so to follow along in these demos
you can just get Express and use it.
And should the time come when you find, oh I do need something that's in Professional, which costs roughly
around $1,000, a little bit less maybe. And then maybe you discover, oh there is something that I need that's
in Premium, which costs about five times as much as professional or wow, I love this feature in Ultimate and
I am willing to pay double what Premium costs to get Ultimate.
That's fine, that's your choice, but in order to follow along in this material,
you do not need to go out and get one of those versions of Visual Studio.
Now if you happen to own a version of Visual Studio, perhaps because you work in another language and you are
considering adding C++ to your arsenal, you can of course follow along in all of the demos I am going to
show you, using your copy of Visual Studio. Things may look a little different, because Express is a simpler,
stripped down UI with less menus and less options, so my screens may look a little simpler than your screens,
but all the code that works in Express will work in other editions of Visual Studio.
So that's not going to be a problem at all.