Once you have Visual C++ Express installed, you need to learn how to use it.
I am going to show you around it using some code that is already written and that I know runs.
This is the Visual C++ Express product, and there are a lot of, kind of moving parts here that I want to show you.
First, this large or at least largest of them all window, is the sort of main editor pane where you edit your code.
And then there are various tool windows that each have their name, like this one is the output window,
and you can close them with the X, or just unpin them with this pin so that they are down here on a little pane
and you can click them to make them come back up, or close them completely.
This sort of standard configuration, here's the editor and here's my Solution Explorer, is what most people
have open when they're working on a C++ application. Now if you are using a product other than Visual C++ Express,
if you are using some other copy of Visual Studio that you had around, your Solution Explorer may
not be on the left like this, it may be over here on the right.
If you want, you can change your settings in that other application to C++ settings,
and then it will look more like this. Or you can just kind of map between the two as you follow along.
Now there are less menus and tool bars in the Express additions of Visual Studio than in the Pro,
Premium, and Ultimate versions, but there's still plenty of menu items.
And I am not going to walk through all of these and explain them all in turn, I will just show you how to do
some things, and you will start to get comfortable with the menus and with the tool bar options as we go.
So what I have here in the editor window, is a very, very simple C++ application.
No doubt you have heard of the concept of saying hello world as your first application, this is slightly
more sophisticated. It will actually say hello to whoever introduces themselves to it.
And I am going to, before I show you any of the code, simply run it so that you can see how it works.
And in order to run it, I need to use a command that's actually not in the menus for Visual C++ Express,
and that's the run without debugging command.
You can see that there is a perhaps familiar green triangle here labeled Start Debugging (F5).
I don't want to debug this application, I just want to run it, and that's Control+F5,
so I am going to hold Control and press F5.
And my application runs, this is a very large DOS prompt for this size of screen, let me just shrink it a little.
So this DOS prompt or command box is what console applications run in, and it's put some letters on the
screen, it says Type your name. If I type my name and press enter, it says Hello Kate, Press any key to continue.
This is what we call a console application, and all of the IO is in the form of text, either text the program
types to me, or texts that I type back to the program. So I am just going to press a key,
and we have finished running the application and we are now back in Visual C++ Express.
In a little while I am going to explain this code to you in slightly more detail.
But I'd like to start by just kind of taking this as a given and showing you some of what Vision Studio can
do for you before you have to start to learn what all of the different pieces of this code mean.
Programs in C++ are made up of statements, and statements generally speaking, end with a semi-colon, just as
they do in C# and Java and the other languages that we often call semi-colon brace bracket languages.
So I would like to show you what happens if I take the semi-colon off the end of a line where it belongs.
So for example here, if I delete this semi-colon, one thing that happens is that this margin color here
becomes yellow. Green in the margin indicates a saved change and yellow indicates an unsaved change.
So if I click the Save icon up here, it goes back to being green.
The other lines are green because I edited them just before this demo started.
But you may also notice that there is a little red underline here underneath this closed brace bracket.
And if you hover over it, it actually says Error: expected a semi-colon, and this is a compiler error,
happening in the editor before I have deliberately compiled my code.
Let's say for a moment that I didn't spot that red wiggly, I didn't know what it meant, or I just didn't see
it there and I'd like to try compiling my code. Compiling your application, takes your code
and prepares it to be an executable.
Technically speaking, in C++ we have a compile step and then a link step.
Compiling is done once to each of your source files and then linking pulls them all together into an executable.
We only have one source file in here, this Hello.cpp, so we will compile it and then immediately link it together.
And that combination of compiling all of your source files and then linking the resulting objects into an
executable, is known just as build the solution. So on the debug menu, there is this command to
Build Solution and I can select this command. Now you see that at the last line of by build output says
that one failed, 0 succeeded. I have a problem. Let's just pin this in place so that we can see.
In this line of output is my error message. So if I scroll past the path to the file, I can see it's a
syntax error missing semi-colon before brace bracket.
Now it tells you what line the problem happened on, happened on line 16.
And if I put my cursor on line 16, you can see down here that's line 15, column 10, for what that matters, and
the actual problem is on the next line because we hit the brace bracket without adding a semi-colon in between.
But that would be a very poor way to try to find your error messages and deal with them to look for line
numbers and then go in here and move the cursor around until the line number looked right.
All you need to do is just double-click the line with the error on it
and you are taken directly to that line here in the editor.
You also get the message repeated here, syntax error: missing semi-colon before brace bracket.
So if I fix the mistake by putting the semi-colon back and build again, you can see that it succeeded.
One succeeded, zero failed. I want to just keep making pretty much the same edit and carrying forward so
that you can see some of the things that Vision Studio does for you automatically.
If I edit away the semi-colon again, this time we have a little more time to look around and notice some other things.
There's a star that shows up here on the name of this file. If you have many files open at once, one of
them is sort of current at a time, and it is highlighted like this, but any with unsaved changes
will have this star on them. And if you save them by clicking the Save button,
then the changes will obviously be saved, the star will go away, the yellow will turn to green and so on.
What a lot of people don't know, is that when you build with unsaved changes like this,
it is saved for you automatically. So you saw the yellow turned green, the star went away,
and it automatically saved our change as part of the build process. So you don't need to save and then build.
If you are a really confident person or you've gotten used to looking for those red wiggly underlines and you
know that when they are not there you are pretty much going to run successfully,
you can just go straight to running without building first.
So if I use Control+F5 to run the application, it says all of this is out of date,
would you like to build it? And you can even say I want to always build it, don't show this again.
Whether you say yes or no, then that will be your answer for all time.
I am just going to say yes without ticking the box. So it saves everything, builds everything,
and it is going to work and then it will immediately run and greet me.
So at this point, you know how to edit code, you know how to build code, and you know how to run code without debugging.
I just want to take a moment and show you why I have been running without debugging.
If I just click the green triangle to start debugging, but I don't have any breakpoints or any places inside
my code for it to stop, the application will just run and then terminate because it is finished.
So I'll run it. I get a slightly smaller font here because my debug settings are a little different from my
non-debug ones, but I'll enter my name. And it's gone, and you are like, where did my app go?
I didn't get to see my output. Well because it just finished, you didn't have any breakpoints.
So there are some ways to get around this, like putting a breakpoint in your application for no other reason
than to give you a chance to read the output. Or putting a statement in your code that causes it to stop and wait.
The way I deal with this is I just use Control+F5, and then you automatically get that press any key to continue.
That's what works for me and that's what I am going to be doing in the demos for you.