C++ is a general purpose programming language. It can be used to write a wide variety of different applications.
So you could create a Windows application, that's something with, you know buttons and text boxes and drop downs,
the kinds of controls that you are maybe used to interacting with in a Windows application.
It can also be used to write console applications, which is what I just showed you in the demonstration.
They write text to the screen, they read text from the screen.
Interesting thing about a console application in contrast to a Windows application
is that they only sort of listen to you typing on the keyboard when they decide they want to.
So, it says enter your name and then it is sitting there listening and waiting for you to type your name.
At other times you can type all you like and the application would not be listening and would not react to that.
Whereas in a Windows application, very often you can type anytime, anywhere without waiting to be prompted.
You can press F keys, you can click things with the mouse and the application is going to kind of react to that.
You can also build in C++ services and servers, things that don't even have a user interface at all,
they just kind of run on the machine and they react to requests coming in,
typically from other applications or to things happening on the computer.
And you can write libraries, which is basically reusable code for other applications to leverage.
The console applications are the simplest for us to deal with because there're really just working with text.
Text to the screen, text from the keyboard. They don't have to show how to draw lines, circles, squares,
how to build controls, how to interact with Windows, how to react to being interrupted by user input at any time.
We can focus on just the syntax of the language. Where does the semi-colon go?
What is the name of this piece of the language and why does it look like that?
Without having to learn how Windows works or the rules for how to draw really great three dimensional
graphics with a glow and transparency and so on. Those are the applications that we're going to be working with,
just as ways of demonstrating the language. Console applications are all about text and usually very
very simple calculations, so that you can focus on what you need to learn about syntax, punctuation,
and some of the other things that may be new to you.