This module has been about getting you ready to start to learn the building blocks of any C++ application.
So to start with, I would encourage you to go and get Visual C++ Express.
If you have another version of Visual Studio, that's great, but Visual C++ Express is free and it will work
fine for all of the demos that we are doing. And its relatively a straight forward application to use and to
get comfortable and familiar with. Because it's an integrated development environment, you can edit your code.
You can see those red wigglies when you make a mistake while you are editing your code.
You can build as a combination of compiling and linking.
It's not really terribly important at the moment to understand them.
When you start to get errors, you need to be able to understand the difference between a compiler error
and a linker error and we will talk about those as we go.
And you see how to run an application without debugging or with debugging, and the possible problem
when you are running a console application, that if you run without debugging,
it just kind of runs out the end and you don't see the output.
And how running without debugging causes, Visual Studio will pause it for you, give you a chance to read the output.
That's generally what we are going to want to do. Because console applications are the simplest,
that's what all the demos in this course are going to be, and that's what you are going to be using to get
comfortable and familiar with the syntax of the language and the way that applications come together.