There are two ways to write an overload: as a member function of whatever type is before the operator and
the function takes an instance of the type that's after the operator, or as a free function, it's not in any
class, that takes two parameters, the first, the type that's before the operator, and the second, the type
that's after it. When it's your class you should always try to write it the member function way, so if
you've written some MyClass and you want to be able to say, is my object less than some other thing?
Is this order less than a different order? You write a function called operator&lt; and if you're writing an
overload for operator plus or operator times or operator +=, all of which can be overloaded, then those are
the names you give. The return type of the comparison operator is less than, less than or equal to, is equal
to, is always Boolean true or false. The return type of the other operators is not a Boolean.
For example, when I add two numbers I get a number. If I take a date and add a number to it I would expect
to get a date. If I take two dates and subtract them I probably don't expect to get a date back right?
I probably expect to get a number back, so you have to think about what the return types are.
For the comparisons, it's Boolean, true or false. This is a member function of MyClass and the parameter that
it takes is of type OtherType, whatever it is I'm going to compare to.
If it makes sense to compare two dates, I might write an operator that just takes a date.
If I am going to say is this order less than 100, then I guess I have to write an operator that takes an
integer. Very common for the comparison operators that they just take the same type, so you compare two
dates, compare two orders, compare two deals, but the compiler won't stop you from comparing a date to a
string if you can figure out a smart way to do that. What about the case where you don't own the type that's
before the operator? So something that you don't own -- could be an integer; nobody owns integer.
Could be string, the Standard Library owns string, or could just be some other class within your system, but
that you're not the developer of and you want to be able to say is something less than my object?
You can't go into the other type class and add an operator less than, so you have to write a free function.
Returns bool because this is operator&lt;, returns true or false.
Its name is still operator&lt;, but notice it no longer has the full class name:: because it's not;
it's just a free function; it's not in a class; and it takes two parameters.
The first one is the type that's before the operator, the second is the type that's after the operator.
Now this is not part of my class, so if it needs to get to any member variables of my class it's probably
going to have to get at them through public functions. There is a way around that with something called friend,
I'll show you it in the demo, but it's not your first choice. If there are public function's available,
that's what you should use. It looks complicated when you try to write it out generically.
It's actually really simple when you go to write one, so let me show you how.