I've written some overloads of the comparison operator so that you can take a look at
how they're actually coded. First though, I want you to see how they're used because it's pretty simple and
intuitive. I've got two people here, p1 and p2, and if you remember how these objects work, they have a
first name, a last name, and an arbitrarynumber, and these constructors are setting their arbitrary numbers
to 123 and 456 respectively. Then I'm going to test whether or not p1 is less than p2 and if it's
not I'm going to print out the word not, so this'll pump out either p1 is less than p2 or p1 is not less than
p2. If we look at the values, if we're going alphabetically, k is before s in the alphabet.
If we are going by numerical value of the arbitrarynumber, 123 is less than 456, so I'd expect this to print
out p1 is less than p2. Now I'm going to compare p1 to a number, an integer, 300.
That sort of tells us, just by reading the code, that it's probably the arbitrarynumber that's being
compared. Pretty much the identical code, except this says 300 here instead of p2.
Well 123 is less than 300, so I'm guessing to see that this would say p1 is less than 300, and then we flip
it around and ask is 300 less than p1. This isn't just about getting the opposite answer, as you saw on the
slide, this also means we actually get a different function called.
When the compiler needs to deal with this line of code it's going to call a function, which is a member of
the Person class, called operator&lt;, that takes a person as its single argument.
When it comes time to deal with this line of code it's going to call a member function of person, called
operator&lt;, that takes an integer for its single argument. When it needs to deal with this line of code it
can't find a member function of integer, so it's going to look for a free function called operator&lt;, that
isn't in any class at all, whose first argument is an integer, and whose second argument is a person, and as
the person developer you sort of have to cross your fingers that nobody else feels like writing that
function. I've written those three and I've declared them all in person.h and implemented them all in
person.cpp, so let me show them to you now.
The two member functions, one that takes a person and one that takes an integer, are inside the person class.
I've defined these as member functions of Person. Person class starts here, ends here, and these are public
member functions. Now I decided to make this one take a Person reference rather than a person.
When we were talking about functions and about passing by value versus passing by reference,
it's a little quicker to pass by reference.
In fact, there are a series of idioms and patterns that we use when we're writing
operator overloads and we use references for a number of reasons, actually have a pattern to use const
reference, but since we haven't talked about const yet I'm not going to bring that in, but I have written it
to take a person reference, and this one takes an integer. The third function, same name, operator&lt;, same
return type, bool, but it takes two parameters, the integer first and then the person, and that's the one
that's used in this comparison here. Now the three functions are all implemented in the Person.cpp class.
There's no particular rule about where you have to put free functions.
I would never take all my free functions from throughout my application and stick them all in one big file
called functions. This overload, it may not be part of the Person class, but it should be maintained by the
Person developer. It should be written by someone who knows how Person works, and it really belongs in
Person.h because anyone who includes Person.h is probably going to need this function.
Similarly, the code for it belongs in Person.cpp. We start with functions that you've seen before from the
other demos using Person. Let's come down here to the new ones.
This operator&lt; is part of the Person class. We call it by its full name, Person:: and it takes a person
reference and it just returns whether or not the arbitrarynumber of the person instance the method was
called on, that is to say the guy before the operator, is less than the other guy's arbitrarynumber.
You could add a more complicated application, but I have to tell you, when I look at comparison operators
in the wild they're generally all like this. They're a single line long.
They say, return whether the person's salary is greater than the other person's salary.
Return whether or not the order total, how that compares to the other order's total or the ship date or the
due date or some other single variable. Sometimes you might see a little tie-breaking or a tiny bit of a
calculation, but it's common as dirt for these comparison operators to be just really one line of code.
(Typing) The one that takes an integer, so we were saying if p1 is less than 300, just compares the member
variable of the instance that was before the operator to the number.
And the free function, notice its name does not start person::,
it just compares the two parameters that it was given, in this case, the integer and
the arbitrarynumber of the person. You see that I'm using this public function, GetNumber.
That's because this operator&lt; is a free function. It's not in the Person class.
It can't access arbitrarynumber directly. arbitrarynumber is private, so I have to use this public GetNumber.
Let's run this to show that it works.
p1, which was 123, is less than p2, which was 456. Yep. p1 is less than 300; yes, 123 is less than 300,
and 300 is not less than p1, also correct, so all of these operators work.
It's a good sign. As a rule of thumb, if you're going to implement less than you should probably also
implement greater than. You should consider implementing less than or equal to, greater than or equal to, is
equal to, and so on. People will be very confused if they can only use one operator and not all the rest of
them and it's quite common to implement these in terms of each other.
I'm not going to show you all of that, just in the interest of time.
I do want to consider the possibility, what would you do if there was no public GetNumber function in Person?
This is a completely fake and arbitrary thing, so you know, we stuck a public function in it a long time ago
for demo purposes, but it's quite common to write business objects that do not reveal their individual
components. If there's a business need for it elsewhere within the application then you would add that
public function, but there may not be a business need for it.
Would you add a public GetNumber function for no other reason than to let this operator work, and if you
didn't, what would be your alternative? Well, in C++, and many other languages don't give this capability,
there is a way around this and the motivation for having a way around it has to do with this unfortunate
circumstance that some of your operator overloads have to be free functions.
They have to be free functions because you can't go into integer and add a method to it, but really,
emotionally, spiritually if you will, this is part of Person. It's here in the same files as all the rest of
the Person code. It's written by the same developer and yes, if I change this variable's name I'm going to
have to rewrite all the Person code. I get that and you know what, I'll rewrite this at the same time,
right. Given that I can make an exception to the public private rules for this particular function and copy
this line, come up here and say friend, and then paste the line.
This doesn't declare a function. I still have to declare it down here.
What it does is it says, this is an exception to the rules about what is private and what is public.
It doesn't make operator&lt;, that takes an integer and a person somehow a member function of Person,
but it does give it those privileges and once those privileges have been given to it,
instead of calling this public function GetNumber, I can use this private arbitrarynumber, and I'll
just build this to prove to you that it compiles (Typing)
and indeed, it does. Without the friend statement (Typing)
I get error messages, basically saying I can't access that private member, arbitrarynumber.
The friend statement was what made the exception and that made it possible for that
operator to access the private variable. You may have heard that the friend keyword in C++ breaks
encapsulation and there's no denying it; it does. There I am letting a free function that is not part of
Person access Person's private member variables, but it's not part of Person because of a quirk of the way
the compiler has you write overloads. We've got the header for it here in Person's header.
We've got the code for it here in Person.cpp and if someone comes along and changes the design of Person,
they have a to-do-list of things they need to fix. They need to fix all of the methods that are already in
Person and yeah, they need to fix this one too, and in case they don't happen to see it down here after the
end of the class definition, they'll certainly see it here. This friend forms your to-do-list if you happen
to change some of the private insides. The friend keyword has other uses that are less defendable than this
one. This is 100% A-OK. It's less okay when you have two classes that share a lot of work and golly this is
annoying writing these get things; I think I'll just make them a friend.
That's generally a sign that you have misdesigned your pair of classes.
Don't let what people tell you about that use of friend mess up this use of friend, which is entirely
appropriate and a good practice. If you're writing an operator overload, the only way to write overloads
where your type is not before the operator is to write free functions and in many cases, if you don't have
public functions available to write those free functions with, you're going to use the friend statement to
gain access to the private member variables. It's not wrong.
Let's focus back, not on the complexity of the friend statement, but on the simplicity of this code.
Because you take the time to write those overloads, which are admittedly a little funny,
operator&lt; is a weird function name, you get this super-readable code that uses your object.
You put a little effort into writing your class and now the code that uses your class
makes perfect sense, as much as it can make sense to ask whether one person is less than another, based on the
value of an arbitrarynumber, but imagine you're doing something real, you know dates and purchase orders and
things. Using the &lt; here is more readable and more understandable than using a member function like compare
or is less than all spelled out i-s-l-e-s-s-t-h-a-n. I love operator overloading.
It puts a little effort on the author of a class, but produces very compact and readable code, which is a
good thing.