Pointers are straightforward when the objects that you have a pointer to are just flat objects with no
base class. So far, you've seen pointers to integers, to Person, to Resource.
When you have an inheritance hierarchy then you have to understand the rules around pointers to a base
class and pointers to a derived class. When you do an object-oriented design
you often use the test sentence, is a. So imagine a hierarchy where I have a base class BankAccount,
and some drive classes, CheckingAccount, and SavingAccount.
It's about a 30-year-old example, but it's a goody.
A CheckingAccount is a BankAccount; a savings account is a BankAccount; and if some function takes a
BankAccount pointer, you can pass down a savings account pointer, or a CheckingAccount pointer, and that
function shouldn't complain in any way. It's a Liskov substitutability and in C++ it's done with pointers.
The function takes a BankAccount pointer. I give it a CheckingAccount pointer.
It thinks of it as a BankAccount pointer, stores it in that base class pointer, and then, obviously,
calls only base class functions using the pointer. I haven't designed BankAccount.
I just started talking about it, but imagine it's got GetBalance.
That's a function in the base class. It will be in the drived classes.
Both CheckingAccount and SavingAccount will have a GetBalance and so, this code that expects a
BankAccount pointer can go ahead and call GetBalance in total confidence.
It's guaranteed to work, but a question arises. What code will run?
In a lot of languages you may think you know the answer. Oh, it's the more derived implementation in the
subclass. In C++ it's up to the programmer. You decide when you write BankAccount whether GetBalance is
virtual or not. If it's virtual then the derived class version of the function will run, so SavingAccount
GetBalance or CheckingAccount GetBalance, but if the author of BankAccount made GetBalance non-virtual, which
is the default because it's the fastest, then only the BankAccount version will be executed,
even when the object in question is really a SavingsAccount or really a CheckingAccount.
You as the developer get to choose whether you want virtual functions or non-virtual functions.
In C++ virtual functions are implemented through a virtual table, which is a little collection of memory
that has the name of the function and where to find the code for it.
You don't really care and, in fact, the standard doesn't insist on it working this way, but the point is,
at runtime there's a little bit of a cost of figuring out what function to run, and your program is a
little bit bigger because of the memory taken up by the virtual table.
If your class has no virtual functions at all it will be a little bit smaller and run a little faster, and,
in some cases, people want that, so you get to choose virtual or not virtual.
Now, this relationship based in derived only works in one direction, so you can't take a BankAccount pointer
and hand it to something that's expecting a CheckingAccount pointer.
That's not fair. Checking accounts might have, I don't know, overdraft limit and your bank account doesn't
have that, so a pointer to an actual bank account can only be given to code that's expecting an actual
bank account, not to something expecting a checking account, but a pointer to a checking account can always
be given to code expecting a bank account because a checking account is a bank account.
Interestingly, when you use smart pointers, like shared_ptr and unique_ptr, you can get this same
polymorphism preserved, exactly the same behavior as if you were using raw pointers.
Since I consider using smart pointers to be a best practice, I want to make sure that you know you're not
giving anything up when you use them in an inheritance hierarchy.