We've been using the Person and Tweeter hierarchy throughout this material.
Let's use it again.
Here I have a very simple console app that's going to create some pointers to Person objects and Tweeter
objects, and it's going to make a bunch of method calls on those pointers.
There are a lot of different versions of Person kicking around, depending on what I want to demonstrate.
Let me just quickly show you the
header file for Person. It just has firstname, lastname, arbitrarynumber,
doesn't really have any operator overloads or anything much going on, and has some Get and Set functions
here -- GetName, GetNumber, SetNumber, and SetFirstName -- and these are just easy functions for me to call
and see what happens within the class.
Tweeter
inherits from Person and has this overload of GetName. Any two functions with the same name we call
overloading, even if they're in entirely different and unrelated classes, so we have operator overloads and
this is certainly an overload. We have GetName here in Person and in Tweeter, and there's been a number of
objects and classes showing up over time in demos with GetName functions in them.
With GetName, in addition to being an overload, is also an override.
I want the Tweeter GetName to be somehow different from the Person GetName, so let's be reminded of what the
Person's GetName does. It just returns the firstname and then a space and then the lastname.
In here we have an attempt at writing a Tweeter GetName. We'll go with the firstname, the lastname, and the
twitterhandle, but you notice there are red wiggles. If I hover over them they say, Error, Personlastname
bla bla bla bla bla is inaccessible, and the same for Personfirstname, inaccessible.
Let's go back to Person.
Right. They're private. Private member variables are not accessible by any code outside the class.
I have a couple of options for how to make this right. One, would be to add individual GetFirstName and
GetLastName public functions to Person for no other reason than to let Tweeter call them.
That's a bad idea. I see people do it a lot, but it's a bad idea.
Another would be to change this private to protected. (Typing)
Protected is a language keyword that says it's private unless the code is in a class that inherits from this class,
then it can do what it likes and party on the data. I consider protected to be a to-do list.
Right now GetName returns firstname space lastname, but if you have a business requirement
to suddenly change that to lastname comma space firstname, if these variables are protected,
you're going to have to go looking for GetName elsewhere in classes that inherit from Person
and depending on your platform architecture it may be a challenge to find all the classes that inherit from
Person and change them to print out first names and last names the new, approved way.
My preference: leave this private and use this perfectly good GetName function that's already been
written. That way, if anyone ever changes GetName in the base class we'll get the changed behavior in the
derived class, much smarter. I'll just go back into Tweeter.cpp
take these, and what I want is to call Person's GetName. (Typing)
Where am I going to get a Person object to use the dot syntax on, some pdot GetName?
Well, I don't have one, but I can still call it from in here by using its full name. (Typing)
Return Person GetName. Now, I'm in a position where if someone makes a change in the base class I'll just
naturally get that change in the derived class. I don't have to worry about private and protected anymore.
I'm not trying to talk to private variables. This is all good.
That makes my project compile, but that wasn't really what we came here for, right?
We really came here to see what happens if I talk to some objects using different kinds of pointers,
so let's go back
and look at this in main. I'm creating a Person on the free store and, by the way, forgetting to delete it.
It's a deliberate memory leak here. I'm creating a Tweeter, also on the free store, which I do remember
to delete, and I'm creating a Person pointer that's equal to this Tweeter pointer, so just two ways of
looking at the same piece of memory out on the free store. And then, I'm going to call GetName on the Kate
pointer that I got from newing up a Person on the KateGregcons pointer, which is a Tweeter pointer that I got
from newing up a Tweeter, and on the pKateGregcons, which is a Person pointer that came from newing up a
Tweeter. Remember that the Person GetName just prints their name; the Tweeter GetName prints their handle
as well. Let's run this,
and here's what happens. When I use the Person pointer, which is pointing to a real Person object, not
surprisingly, I get Person output. When I use the Tweeter pointer, which is pointing to a real Tweeter
object, not surprisingly, I get Tweeter output. When I use a Person pointer, which is really pointing to a
Tweeter, I get Person output. Some of you might have expected differently, but GetName in Person.h
is not virtual, and because it's not virtual I will always get Person output.
If I want to see a Tweeter code for GetName run even when I'm using a Person pointer, as long as it's really
a Tweeter object that the Person pointer is pointing to, I need to make GetName virtual.
Now, I'll only need to do this here in the base class. I don't need to do it in Tweeter.
You can if you want as a form of documentation. And I don't need to do it throughout all of the inheritance hierarchy.
I can just make this single change here and then just run it,
and you see now the Tweeter code ran even though we were using a Person pointer because it really points to
a Tweeter object, and when the function's virtual that's what drives it.
Once I have a virtual function in Person I will have a virtual table and I will take that small performance
hit. At that point, a rule kicks in. Now it's not a compiler rule.
I don't have any warnings from the compiler. This is a best practices rule.
I want you to kind of go on a thought experiment with me. Imagine
that I new this Tweeter up and I don't call delete using the Tweeter pointer, but instead I call delete
using the Person pointer that points to the same place. The destructor for Person and Tweeter is currently
non-virtual.
Here is a destructor. This destructor actually doesn't do anything and we'd be better off taking it away,
but bear with me. We have this destructor; it's not virtual.
If instead of deleting the Tweeter pointer, we called delete on the Person pointer, you know what would happen?
The Person destructor would run. So what? Well, it depends on the class.
If Tweeter manages something, like it opens a file, and its destructor needs to close the file, and I delete
a Tweeter object using a Person pointer, I still want to run the Tweeter destructor.
I still want to close the file or release the lock or let go of the database connection or whatever my
destructor's going to do. How can I prevent this leak where we called the wrong destructor?
How can I be sure that if the object being deleted is really a Tweeter object that the Tweeter destructor
runs? By having the destructor be virtual. Now some people
go so far as to say that all destructors should be virtual. (Typing)
I don't agree with that. That just makes the overhead of virtual functions come into every class
whether they're needed or not, but a really good rule is the minute you have one virtual function,
clearly you're expecting to be using pointers and an inheritance hierarchy, and for virtuality to matter.
There's a really good chance that somebody might call delete on a Person pointer that was really pointing to
a Tweeter object, and despite the fact that as the Person author I have no idea what might get added to Tweeter,
I feel safest making the destructor virtual at this point.
Don't make the destructor virtual before there are any other virtual functions,
but the minute there's one virtual function get in there and make the destructor virtual.
It will save you from a really subtle bug that is extraordinarily hard to track down if you don't just
happen to recognize this pattern and this best practice.