Let's change this demo from using raw pointers, Person* and Tweeter*, to using shared_ptrs.
I'll include memory. (Typing) That brings me in the shared_ptr and since I already have using namespace std
I can just call it shared_ptr. Let's (Typing) make a shared_ptr (Typing) of Person (Typing), and call it
shared pointer to Kate. And there's a couple different ways -- we used to make shared in other demos
because we weren't declaring and initializing the pointer at the same time.
Here, I can, if I wish, simply new up a Person and put it in here
or I can use =make_shared (Typing) at Person (Typing)
and again, pass in those arguments. I'm just going to steal these arguments (Typing)
and I'll put an S and a P. We're not going to be very pronounceable, but we'll be able to tell our objects
apart. (Typing)
This line of code compiles. I'll build it to prove it to you, but it's a little repetitive.
Why do I have to say the type here and here? Interestingly, make_shared a Person returns a
shared_ptr of Person and in C++ 11 we have this cool capability, which is, I don't have to type out the type
of an object if the compiler knows what it is. Here, I can actually use this C++ 11 keyword, auto.
When I do that, if I hover over spKate, you'll see it's a shared_ptr of Person.
It has a type; I just didn't have to come up with it. Its type is whatever make_shared returns.
I can, of course, interact with this pointer the same way we did with the raw ones.
So I could take this line, (Typing) paste it here, and all I need to do is change the variable to spKate,
and that's just fine. I'm dereferencing the shared_ptr to call its GetName function.
I could also go back to calling this a shared_ptr (Typing) to Person, but create it, not by calling
make_shared of Person, but by calling make_shared of Tweeter. So this will now be a shared_ptr to Person
that's actually pointing to an object that was allocated out on the free store as a Tweeter.
I'm going to need another
parameter to my constructor for a twitter handle. (Typing) And if I run this
you can see I got the Tweeter version of GetName. In other words, our shared_ptrs are being appropriately
polymorphic. A shared_ptr of Person that really points at a Person, you get the Person code.
No surprise there. A shared_ptr of Person that really points at a Tweeter, you get the Tweeter code because
it's a virtual function. It just works exactly like a raw pointer.