Let's go back into this same project and add some code that copies some objects around so you can see some
slicing and some compiler error messages.
In the interest of not watching me type, I'll just quickly paste this in.
Here I'm creating a local Person in local storage, passing the parameters into the constructor as always.
This is fine. There's no problem with this line. On the next line I'm trying to create a Tweeter locally
and initialize it by just copying that Person into it. And you see that the error here is, no suitable
user-defined conversion from Person to Tweeter exists. It can make a Person from a Person; it can make a
Tweeter from a Tweeter, but in order to make a Tweeter from a Person I would have to write some code to
teach it how to do that because what are we going to use for the twitter handle?
Let's come in at the other way then. Since that's not going to work let's make a local Tweeter (Typing) and
(Typing) make up a twitter handle, and again, apologies if that's anybody's real twitter handle,
and then let's make a Person (Typing) from that (Typing)
and then I'll use its GetName. (Typing)
What actually happens when this runs is that we copy the firstname, the lastname, and the arbitrarynumber
from localT2 into localP2 and throw away the twitterhandle, since we have no place to put it.
When we call GetName it calls the Person version of GetName. (Typing)
Just says Local Tweeter. There is no handle
and that's because the handle is long gone. Now one way around this would be, I could've made this a Person
pointer; I could've asked for the address of local2; (Typing) and I could have switched from the dot
notation (Typing) to the arrow notation. That'll compile, but it's a lot of work, especially if I had more
than one line of code. Plus, that's a raw pointer. Maybe I should be using a shared_ptr.
Here's a nicer way to get polymorphism while still keeping this syntax.
I can make this a Person reference. One character I type. Run it.
Now I get the Tweeter version of the function
even though I use the Person reference, and that's because references are polymorphic in the same way that
pointers are polymorphic. And I didn't have to go around with stars and ampersands and arrows and all of the
things that start to get people sort of punctuation-tense. It's okay.
Just make it a Person reference. It's a polymorphic reference.
It'll use the Tweeter GetName when I call the function.
Same thing happens if you take a function that takes a Person by reference and you actually give
it a Tweeter, and then it happens to call some member functions of Tweeter.
That's what we'll run, Tweeter member functions, even though the code that's running thinks it's calling
Person member functions. Course, they have to be functions that were defined in Person and furthermore,
were defined as virtual in Person, not just an extra thing like tweet that you added to Tweeter.
It has to be something from Person like GetName, but then you will get the behavior you want.