I want to go back to casting again. A long, long time ago I showed you how to cast with the round brackets.
You have a floating point number and you write round bracket int, round bracket, and then the floating point
number, and then that casts it to an integer, maybe throws away the part of the number that was after the
decimal point. You don't get a warning because hey, you told the compiler you knew what you were doing.
You can use round casts to go back and forth between different kinds of pointers, different kinds of
references, but it's kind of a dangerous thing to do. There's nothing to check to see that it's okay what
you're doing, and when someone else reads over your code they may not understand what you're doing or why
you're doing it, and very often people end up putting comments like, this is okay because I know it actually
has a Tweeter in it. There are better casts available to you, and now that you understand template syntax,
you can use them. Here is the static_cast. It's a template. It's an operator called static_cast, angle
bracket, whatever you want to cast to, and it's done at compile time.
If, at compile time, the compiler doesn't see a relationship between what something's really pointing to and
what you're trying to cast it to, or in the case of numbers, the kind of number it really holds, and the kind
of number you're trying to cast it to, you will get a warning, or in some cases, an error that they're
incompatible. But if it could sometimes hold this kind of information, and could sometimes hold that kind of
information, you can be tripped up by a static_cast because there are no runtime checks to help you out.
The dynamic_cast has a runtime check and the runtime check relies on knowing what the type is at runtime.
It's restricted to working with pointers to objects of classes that have virtual tables.
The cool thing about a dynamic_cast is that when you're trying to cast to a pointer, if it doesn't work,
because at runtime it can be established that, that's not really pointing to a Tweeter, you get back a
nullptr and you can test against a nullptr. If you're trying to cast to a reference it'll throw an
exception. That's okay too. They're slower, to use the dynamic_cast, but it's safer.
You won't ever misinterpret bits and cause really weird bugs of the kind that you can get when you misuse a
static_cast. Now, for the sake of completeness, I'll also mention const_cast.
I'm not showing you the exact syntax here. This is where you can actually take a const variable and cast it
to a not-const variable so you can change it. As you can imagine, not a beginner technique.
Sometimes people will do this to handle caches and things like that, where you're not really changing the
object. There are other ways to do it. Anyway, not for beginners.
Reinterpret_cast is totally not for beginners. This is a matter of bit-twiddling.
This involves knowing how long certain data types are and the pattern of bits inside the data type, and you
say, oh yeah, I think of that as being an integer, and then you put some values in, and then you say, now
I'm going to think of it as being something completely different and ask about its value, and the bits will
be interpreted differently; the meaning will be interpreted differently.
There is old code that uses reinterpret_cast, but what I really use it as is a huge red flag to say, wait a
minute, someone's trying to be really smart here. Is that actually necessary?
That's one of the ways that casts can really express your intent. A static_cast is nice and safe between
two related types and you're really confident that this Person pointer actually points to a Tweeter, so you
just feel like casting it to a Tweeter so you can call some Tweeter function.
Yeah. Dynamic_cast, a little less safe, a little bit of a runtime performance hit, but you will be checked
on, and you will be protected. Const_cast, very dangerous, and reinterpret_cast, extraordinarily dangerous.
This is the shooting your own foot off territory of C++ and that's why I'm not going to teach you how to do
it. I want you to know that it's there. If you see these casts in someone else's code, tread carefully.